<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The stable trveths of the Kirk reqvire a svtable behaviour holden forth by way of sermon upon I. Tim. 3. vers. 14. 15., delivered by Mr. William Dowglas ... before the provinciall Synod of Aberdene, April 18. 1659.</title>
            <author>Dowglas, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36449</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36099</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15603128</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15603128</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104070</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36449)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104070)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1590:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The stable trveths of the Kirk reqvire a svtable behaviour holden forth by way of sermon upon I. Tim. 3. vers. 14. 15., delivered by Mr. William Dowglas ... before the provinciall Synod of Aberdene, April 18. 1659.</title>
                  <author>Dowglas, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4, 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.B. in March ...</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Aberdene :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [2] at beginning.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, III, 14-15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, Scottish.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:104070:1"/>
            <p>THE STABLE TRVETHS OF THE KIRK REQVIRE A SV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TABLE BEHAVIOUR.</p>
            <p>Holden forth by way of <hi>SERMON</hi> upon <hi>I. Tim. 3. Verſ.</hi> 14. 15. delivered by Mr. <hi>William Dowglas</hi> PROFESSOR of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity</hi> in Kings <hi>Colledge,</hi> in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Aberden,</hi> before the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> APRIL 18. 1659.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 25. 5.</bibl> Leade mee in thy truth, and teach mee:</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 50. 23.</bibl> —and to him that ordereth his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation aright, will I shew the ſalvation of God.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>John 17. 17,</bibl> Sanctifie them through thy truth: thy word is truth.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Act. 26. 25.</bibl> But he ſaid, I am not mad, moſt noble <hi>Feſtus,</hi> but ſpeak forth the words of truth and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſſe.</q>
            <p>ABERDENE, PRINTED by <hi>J. B.</hi> in <hi>March,</hi> Ann. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:104070:2"/>
            <head>Some <hi>Eſcapes</hi> to be thus amended.</head>
            <p>Page, 18. lin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. reade enervats. and l. 35. r. then it is a. pag. 19. l. 39 r. propoſe. pag 23. l. 30. r. <hi>declarations.</hi> pag. 26. l. 5. 8. infalliblie. pag. 28. l 27. adde the word <hi>by.</hi> pag. 29. l. 18. r. concluding. pag. 34. l. 4. r. concernment. ibid. l. 37. r. <hi>vnue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aries. pag.</hi> 38. l. 19. r. inveigh. pag. 43. l. 28. r. feed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104070:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable and his ſingular good <hi>Lord,</hi> My <hi>Lord Duffus,</hi> the Author wiſheth ſuch ſufficiencie of <hi>Grace,</hi> as may bring to fulneſſe of <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF true <hi>Piety,</hi> if high eſteeme of <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> if love to the forme of ſound words holding ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſaving trueths,</hi> if due reſpect to the <hi>faithfull Miniſters</hi> of CHRIST, if well purchaſed <hi>Honour,</hi> if cloſe <hi>walking with GOD,</hi> if ingenuous and honeſt <hi>actings</hi> for the good OLD CAUSE, may be ſtrong inducements to make vſe of ſuch a <hi>Patron</hi> then for all theſe jointly, let mee be bold humbly to deſire, to preſent the following thoughts to publick view, under the <hi>Patrocinie</hi> of your L. honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Name. When theſe <hi>graces</hi> in your L. have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared you, to all the Lovers of precious <hi>trueths</hi> in theſe parts, then why not mee alſo? IT was the earneſt deſire of ſome Reverend and godly Miniſters both by <hi>word</hi> and <hi>writte,</hi> that my thoughts upon theſe <hi>verſes</hi> 14 15 of <hi>I. Tim. Chap.</hi> 3. ſhould bee publiſhed; wherein, though through much weaknes I confeſſe. I have endeavoured to vindicat &amp; cleare diverſe precious <hi>ſaving trueths,</hi> which to make out, it behoved me to inlarge ſome points more fully, then were in <hi>Sermon</hi> delivered, wherein my chiefe aime hath been, the juſt oppoſing of <hi>Popery</hi> and other <hi>Novations,</hi> the <hi>Aſſertors</hi> and <hi>Fomenters</hi> whereof with a mouth full and foule, have poured out all manner of <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie</hi> and <hi>Contempt</hi> upon Goſpel-trueths, and the holy Miniſtery, ſo to render both <hi>odious, vſeleſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>ineffectuall:</hi> which with our own preſent <hi>Coldneſſe</hi> and <hi>Indifferencie</hi> in the things of GOD, and the not ſiſting of needleſſe <hi>debates,</hi> together with our <hi>barrenneſſe,</hi> and <hi>walking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſutable,</hi> and <hi>behaviour unanſwerable</hi> to the GOSPEL of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104070:3"/> CHRIST, ſpeak no leſſe then the <hi>removing of the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick,</hi> or ſome great eclipſe of <hi>Religion</hi> among us. I have ſhunned all juſt offence in owning theſe <hi>trueths;</hi> if any charge <hi>aſperitie,</hi> let theſe know, that were it not, <hi>That love covereth many blemiſhes,</hi> much more might have been ſpoken. If any profeſſe <hi>unſatisfaction</hi> in ſome things here, let me tell them, <hi>That I ſpeak the truth in CHRIST, that I am for peace, but doth not ſeek to pleaſe men.</hi> I ſhall ſpare to adde more, onely this, That recommending this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> both to your L. favourable <hi>acceptance,</hi> and judicious <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure:</hi> and hoping that your L. will regard the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>matter,</hi> &amp; accept the minde of the <hi>Offerer.</hi> I reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend your L. to the rich <hi>Grace</hi> of GOD. <hi>who hath called you to the unfained love of the trueth, and is able to preſerve you unblameable therein to the end;</hi> I do ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your L. moſt humble ſervant in the Lord, Mr. William Dowglas.</signed>
               <dateline>At old <hi>Aberdene</hi> 
                  <date>March 30. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:104070:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Delivered by Mr. <hi>VVilliam Dowglas</hi> PROFESSOR of <hi>Divinity</hi> in Kings <hi>Colledge,</hi> before the Provinciall Synod of ABERDENE, <hi>Aprile</hi> 18. 1659.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl> Upon I. TIM. Verſ. 14. 15.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Theſe things write I unto thee, hoping to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee ſhortlie.</p>
                  <p>But if I tarry long, that thou mayeſt know, how thou oughtest to behave thy ſelf in the houſe of GOD, Which is the Church of the living GOD, the pillar and ground of the trueth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this firſt Epiſtle, The Apoſtle worthily acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe three wayes. Firſt, as a <hi>Paſtor</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing <hi>Timothy,</hi> both anent the right end of the LAW: as alſo what <hi>Goſpel-Trueths</hi> are to bee taught, profeſſed, and practiſed, and withall urging his proficiencie in them, as in Chap. 1. and 2. Secondly, as a <hi>Prophet,</hi> fortelling dangerous approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing times, ſad Apoſtaſie, totall or partiall, as Chap. 4. &amp;c. Thirdly, as an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> preſcribing Rules anent the oeconomie of the true Viſible Church, and emitting Canons anent Office-bearers, Biſhops and Deacons in that Church, as in chap. 3. of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104070:4"/> which the TEXT is.</p>
            <p>In it are two points conſiderable, I. a <hi>Reaſon</hi> why he iſſues out this <hi>Directory,</hi> which is, <hi>That he might know how &amp;c.</hi> II. U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon <note place="margin">Diviſion of the <hi>Text.</hi>
               </note> the mentioning of his ſutable behaviour, wee have an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant <hi>deſcription</hi> of the Church, by way of Commendation, in that it is, <hi>The houſe of GOD &amp;c. the ground of trueth;</hi> a <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie</hi> of which Trueths we have <hi>verſ.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt ſet down in verſ. 14. and beginning of verſ. 15. in it two remarkable points are expreſſed. 1. The courſe he <note place="margin">Verſ. 14. divided into 2.</note> taketh being abſent. <hi>Theſe things write I unto thee.</hi> 2. The way he purpoſeth to ſupplie that, <hi>hoping to come unto the ſhortly. But if I &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Firſt againe, I ſhall ſhortly take notice but of theſe <note place="margin">In first, are three.</note> three. I. The Courſe, is <hi>writing.</hi> II. Who doeth write? III. Who it is hee writes unto.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt; Scripturall Writtings are for three. 1. For <note place="margin">I. writting for what.</note> Memoriall duration, ſee <hi>Iſai. 30. 8. Exod.</hi> 17. 14. 2. For Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, excitation and Chriſtian edification, ſee <hi>I. Cor. 10. 11. II. Pet.</hi> 3. 1. and <hi>I. John</hi> 2. 14. 20. 3. For the due regulating <note place="margin">Namely for three.</note> of Faith and manners, as <hi>Joh. 5. 39. Joh. 20. 31. II. Tim.</hi> 3. 15. 16. (Whence we may collect, of what ſingular uſe for Unitie &amp; Concord were the <hi>Encyclickes</hi> of the Antient Kirk.) called by AUGUST. <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municaetoriae literae.</hi> But paſſing this, I the rather note the Ends of the Divine writes to ſtoppe <hi>Stappletons</hi> foule mouth, (Who <hi>Contr. 4. q.</hi> 5.) preferreth the <hi>Word-unwritten,</hi> to the <hi>Written,</hi> for three Reſpects. 1. For Authority, in that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written Word,</hi> may define againſt the <hi>Written.</hi> 2. That the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written Word</hi> is of greater certanty for determinations of <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. That the Materialls propoſed in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwritten Word</hi> are more excellent, then theſe in the <hi>Written Word.</hi> The very repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of which blaſphemies may be a juſt refutation of them.</p>
            <p>As to the Second. This is undeniable, that it belonged to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick <note place="margin">II. Who writes</note> function, to emitt Rules for the Church, both in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as alſo in particular. Here briefly take notice of three. 1. It belonged to Apoſtolick juriſdiction, to regulate <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> and <note place="margin">Note three. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Paſtors,</hi> both in their fixed reſidences, ſo we have it <hi>Tit.</hi> 15. as alſo in their neceſſarie excurſions and delegations: for although (as <hi>Gillesp.</hi> q. 4. Miſcell. well notes) for latitude the office of the <hi>Evangelist</hi> was commenſurable with that of an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> yet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104070:4"/> ſo they were not for power of Commiſſion or juriſdiction. 2. is, That accordingly <hi>Paul</hi> indeavours to be uſefull now, that is, <note place="margin">2.</note> by Epiſtolick Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to ſupply the want of his <hi>Perſonall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, comforts</hi> and <hi>conference.</hi> Thus the Fathers of the ancient kirk did, as ſaid is: and this is to leſſon us now, that as occaſion is offered from Providence, we imitate him in this. 3. is, That <note place="margin">3.</note> hence I finde no warrant for <hi>Roman-Reſcripts or papall Decretalls</hi> now; for it were in conſequent to argue from the power of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick Delegations to that of the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> tyrannicall. <hi>Dayes</hi> wer, that <hi>Roman</hi> delegations to ſiſter Churches, as to <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage, Antioch, Millan, Alexandria</hi> were wholſome, but the caſe is altered, as is well noted by <hi>Spalato,</hi> lib. 4. cap. 12. Rep. eccl. <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eolim fuit legatio ſana, poſtea valetudinaria, tandem mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua facta.</hi> Firſt, it was ſound, then languid, laſtly dead and null.</p>
            <p>As for the Third, <hi>unto thee,</hi> whether to him as an <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">III. To whom?</note> or as an ordinarie <hi>Paſtor</hi> at EPHESUS, it matters not much. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie this, he as an inferiour, was to receive Orders from a poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Superiour, as the ſame <hi>Spal.</hi> writes <hi>l. 4. cap. 1. Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> hold him out as the <hi>Angel</hi> of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> or that he was <hi>Moderator, Biſhope</hi> and <hi>Preſident</hi> amongſt the Elders there. I ſhall now onely marke what good account <hi>Paul</hi> gives of him in <hi>Scripture:</hi> And firſt ſee his <hi>Linage, birth</hi> and <hi>bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Who he was</note> II. Tim. 1. 5. ſecondly, <hi>his Calling,</hi> II. Tim. 4. 5. thirdly, <hi>his gifts</hi> and <hi>abilities,</hi> II. Tim. 1. 6. II. Tim. 3. 15. I. Tim. 3. 14. Fourthly, <hi>his diligence</hi> and <hi>fidelitie</hi> in imployments, ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 20. Fifthly, <hi>his strict walking</hi> inſinuated, I. Tim. 5. 25. Whence I note this, Where all theſe concurre, it is an evident ſigne of an inward CALL. The <hi>Madeburg. Centur.</hi> lib. 2. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</hi> 1. cap. 3. hold, as others alſo, That <hi>Hee,</hi> with <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dion. Areopag.</hi> were executed at ROME by <hi>Domitians</hi> command.</p>
            <p>Uſe to be made hereof, is this; Since <hi>Paul</hi> writes to him, then <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Timothy</hi> muſt reade this <hi>ſcript.</hi> both to make him wiſe to ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as alſo to <hi>behave</hi> himſelf as becomes in Gods houſe. Are not all ſcriptures Gods <hi>epiſtles</hi> to men? ſo <hi>Auguſt.</hi> on pſal. 90. <hi>The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is Gods letter dated from that City, to which as pilgrames wee tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell.</hi> The firſt <hi>Nicen Councel</hi> decreed, <hi>That no Chriſtian want a Bible.</hi> CHRYSOST. 3 <hi>Hom.</hi> on <hi>Lazar.</hi> bids the people <hi>take the Bable and reade it.</hi> HIERON in the epitaph of <hi>Paul,</hi> and in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle. to <hi>Laeta, Theodora</hi> &amp;c. affirmeth it <hi>to be unlawfull for women
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104070:5"/> to be ignorant of the ſcriptures, or that one day ſhould paſſe without learning ſomething out of them daylie.</hi> Whoſe teſtimonies I the rather cite againſt theſe two moſt erroneous bold <hi>aſſertions</hi> of the Ieſuite <hi>Stapleton,</hi> Relect. <hi>Cont.</hi> 5. q. 3. a. 4. Firſt, <hi>That the Tranſlation of Scriptures is the ſeminarie of hereſie. 2. That the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſcriptures by the Laicks is impious and pernitious.</hi> O heavens be aſtoniſhed at this!</p>
            <p>The INTENT is, <hi>to come ſhortly to them.</hi> Anent this compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <note place="margin">2. his purpoſe.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I note that ſome as <hi>Aretius</hi> referre it vnto <hi>his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> but others to the neareſt, <hi>his comming.</hi> But the maine <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</hi> of Critiques here, is, That this Comparative addeth much to the ſimple ſignification of the <hi>abſolute;</hi> ſo it is, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 27. ſo <hi>Act.</hi> 25. 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. ſo <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 1. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Since then wee finde his Reſolve is for <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the queſtion is, <hi>Did hee indeed by a locall motion returne to it?</hi> Although ſome for the affirmative ground on the words <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 23. yet the moſt are for the negative<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if ſo, yet his <hi>Intent</hi> is rationall, and for <note place="margin">why to come</note> good vſe, as is well obſerved by judicious <hi>Calvin,</hi> and learned <hi>Danaus.</hi> as 1. to repreſſe inſolent and contumacious Spirits, and to ſober their minds, upon the ſuppoſall of his ſpeedy returne. 2. To refreſh the preſent incumbent, with a comfortable hope, of injoying his perſonall preſence to eaſe and relieve him. 3. To excite <hi>Timothy</hi> and ſtirre him up to further diligence to, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on his <hi>Calling,</hi> ſee the like <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 4. 13. 4. To demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat <hi>Pauls</hi> continued care of the welfare of all the Churches of Chriſt. Now to this verſ. 15. bee ſubjoines a PROVISO, <hi>If his occaſionall affaires ſhould retard him:</hi> yet in the <hi>interim,</hi> make uſe of this <hi>written Directory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe words, <hi>But if I tarry long.</hi> are very well rendered <note place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> by <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> on the place thus, <hi>Whether I come ſooner or later, or in Providence not at all, yet by theſe I minde thee of this,</hi> HOW TO BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAVE THY SELF &amp;c. <hi>do thou duty, follow theſe precepts thus ſet down, or further to be ſet down, applicable to all Pastors &amp; Churches, as to</hi> Timothy <hi>and</hi> Epheſus. Here wee may take notice of thoſe <note place="margin">I. Obſer.</note> two. 1. by this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, wee ſee his promiſed returne to be condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, but not abſolute, as is well noted by <hi>Eſtius.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſayeth <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> on the place. For though all prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> were ſufficiently revealed to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104070:5"/> yet all future and emergent Circumſtances were not clearly revealed. Then waite on duty, ſubmit to providence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre events to God. Diſtinguiſh between Gods diſpoſals and <note place="margin">2. Obj. is an vſe.</note> mans propoſals. The ſpirits impulſe admitts of no repulſe, ſee a cleare inſtance of this, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 7. there the <hi>Holy Ghoſt did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them to preach the word in Aſia,</hi> and <hi>the ſpirit did not ſuffer them to go to Bithynia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to paſſe this as leſſe Materiall, Let us conſider what the <note place="margin">1. The end of writting.</note> Church is, in which a behaviour ſutable is required. In which obſerve theſe two. 1. The <hi>end</hi> of his writting, <hi>that thou mayest know how</hi> &amp;c. 2. The Churches <hi>dignity</hi> (which is the object of this <hi>comely behaviour)</hi> by way of Panegyrick beyond all that can be given to all Arts or ſciences. In the which are thoſe two. 1. Who is the Proprietary of this <hi>Houſe,</hi> and of the <hi>Church.</hi> 2. What is the property or rather office of this houſe and Church, that is, to be <hi>the ground and pillar of the trueth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe the <hi>Object</hi> well known moves and excits to the <note place="margin">2. A deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Object.</note> duty, we ſhal inſiſt on theſe two firſt. Namely, why the Church is called <hi>the houſe of God, the Church of the living God.</hi> with ſome <hi>vſes</hi> of either: then in what ſenſe the Church is indeed and juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called, <hi>the pillar and ground of trueth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the firſt of theſe two titles; <hi>The houſe of God,</hi> the <note place="margin">1. The houſe of God.</note> Church in ſcripture, is compared to a <hi>garden incloſed,</hi> to an <hi>Army,</hi> to a <hi>City,</hi> and here to an <hi>Houſe:</hi> but to that, <hi>of God,</hi> CHRYSOST. affirming the Apoſtle here to allude to <hi>Bethel,</hi> and to the <hi>Temple</hi> of the Lord. Here firſt conſider. Why the Church hath this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, then give ſome <hi>vſes</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, The very origination or ſignification of the <note place="margin">I. Why the Church is ſo called.</note> word in the <hi>Hebrew, Greeke</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> relates to it, as of God. In the firſt, it is <hi>building.</hi> in the ſecond, it is <hi>dwelling.</hi> in the third, it is <hi>defending.</hi> IT is well remarked by <hi>D. Ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mond,</hi> this is a phraſe, taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſpeciall place of Gods preſentiating himſelf. For as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayes, Thoughall the world be his <hi>Dominion,</hi> yet the Church is onely his <hi>Houſe.</hi> For, here Hee <hi>dwels,</hi> here hee <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights</hi> to meete with the pious &amp; devout ſoule, here hee receives their addreſſes, here hee anſwers their petitions, here he is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; <note place="margin">Three-fold hous of God 1. Materiall.</note> and without this houſe, is no ſuch communications, no ſuch intertainment. But further to cleare this, the word, <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> relates either 1. to the <hi>Materiall houſe,</hi> whereof reade
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104070:6"/> I. <hi>King.</hi> 8. ordained as an adminicle to advance <hi>Prayer, praiſe</hi> &amp; <hi>ſacrifices</hi> in it. Or: <hi>Sedgwick</hi> on <hi>pſal.</hi> 23. mantaines this to <note place="margin">Of this hous ar theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces meaned, <hi>luke 19. 46 Eccl.</hi> 4. last</note> be Gods houſe, both for operation and for ſeparation, in that divine duties and ſervices are performed in it, and ſo to be ſet a part, as not to be a <hi>Stable</hi> or an <hi>Aile-houſe.</hi> The primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, after the publick peace of Chriſtendome, ſutably had their <hi>Auditories</hi> and <hi>Oratories.</hi> which the <hi>Grecians</hi> and <hi>Latines</hi> called <hi>Baſilicae,</hi> and <hi>Dominicae.</hi> 2. Is the Coeleſtiall, whereof we we reade 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1. 2. and <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 2. 3. Is the Spirituall, yet <note place="margin">2. Coeleſtiall.</note> Militant, the true Church on earth, both viſible and inviſible; this is here. and of this <hi>houſe,</hi> are alſo theſe places, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 2. 6. <note place="margin">3. Spirituall.</note> 
               <hi>I. Pet. 4. 17. Pſal. 69. 9. Luk. 1. 27. Epheſ. 2. 19. Gal.</hi> 6. 10. This is that houſe where <hi>fatneſſe</hi> is. <hi>pſal.</hi> 36. 8. this is that houſe wher <hi>ſatisfying goodneſſe</hi> is, <hi>pſal.</hi> 65. 4. this is that houſe of <hi>David, luk.</hi> 1. 33. this is that houſe <hi>built on the Rocke,</hi> Matth. 7. 24. this is that houſe where <hi>holineſſe is ſeemly</hi> pſal. 93. 5. here wee <hi>inquire,</hi> pſal. 27. 4. here he remains by <hi>ordinances</hi> and his <hi>spirit,</hi> ſee <hi>I. cor.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>I. Cor. 6. 19. II. Cor. 6. 16. Augustine</hi> yet further holds out the reſemblance thus, 1. A houſe hath the <hi>ground,</hi> the <hi>walls.</hi> the <hi>roofe,</hi> ſo the Church hath <hi>ſaith</hi> to be grounded upon, <hi>hope</hi> to bee erected by, and <hi>love</hi> that covereth, &amp;c. 2. A great houſe hath ſeverall <hi>Office-bearers,</hi> ſo that the Church, <hi>I. Cor. 12. 28. Epheſ.</hi> 4. 11. 12. 3. A great mans houſe, hath <hi>veſſels</hi> and <hi>vt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files</hi> of all, and for all ſorts. Now as God is a great <hi>Honſholder,</hi> Matth. 20. 1. ſo hath he in the Catholick Viſible Church, <hi>veſſels</hi> of diverſe frames, <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 2. 20. 4. In a great houſe is <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> for young and old, poore and rich, weake and ſtrong: ſo it is in this houſe, ſee <hi>Heb. 5. 12. 13. 14. I. Pet. 2. 2. Matth.</hi> 15. 26. <note place="margin">Marke the Differences between God his houſe &amp; ours. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5.</note> 27. 5. In a great houſe, there is but one <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Lord:</hi> ſo here it is, <hi>Epheſ. 33. 22. Eph. 5. 24. Col.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
            <p>But yet further to inlarge the point, marke the great <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences</hi> between Gods <hi>Houſe</hi> and our houſes in theſe. 1. Our <hi>houſes</hi> keepe and defend us: but God keeps and defends His <hi>Houſe,</hi> pſal. 121. 3. 5. 6. pſal. 125. 2. <hi>Iſai. 40. 2. Iſai.</hi> 27. 2. 3. it is not with Gods <hi>houſe</hi> as with that of <hi>dagon, I. Sam.</hi> 5. 4. 2. Our <hi>houſes</hi> locally comprehend us, but no houſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehends God, as <hi>I. Kings</hi> 8. 27. 4. Wee may be abſent from our <hi>houſes</hi> elſwhere: but it is not ſo here, ſee <hi>pſal. 24. 1. Matth. 28. 20. Iſai. 43. 2. Heb.</hi> 13. 5. 5. The ſtrongeſt of our <hi>houſes,</hi> they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104070:6"/> weare away, and are periſhing, as <hi>Amos, 6. 11. Pſal.</hi> 49. 11. 12: but not ſo here. All true Members of this <hi>lower houſe,</hi> or <hi>Militant Church,</hi> though now they be <hi>Viatores,</hi> ſhall be of the <hi>vpper houſe,</hi> or of the Triumphant Church, and <hi>Comprehenſores,</hi> ſee <hi>pſal. 84. 11. The Lord will give grace and glory.</hi> 6. O how farre is this <hi>Houſe</hi> ſurpaſſing all the magnifick <hi>Structures,</hi> all the ſumptuous fabricks of the moſt curious and exquiſite <hi>Architects</hi> of this world? if wee either regard the eminent <hi>Structure,</hi> the <hi>ſituation,</hi> the <hi>accomodation,</hi> the <hi>contrivement,</hi> the <hi>duration,</hi> the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> of its beauty, ſee <hi>pſal. 87. Iſai. 26. 1. 2. Heb. 11. 10. Rev.</hi> 21, &amp;c. Never talk of the Perſian <hi>Hiſpaan,</hi> the Ethiopian <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara,</hi> the Egyptian <hi>Pyramids,</hi> the Adrian <hi>Mole,</hi> or the <hi>Lorenzo</hi> in <hi>Spayn,</hi> for in compariſon with this, <hi>They are but as the drope of the bucket compared to the ſea,</hi> or <hi>as the duſt of the ballance com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the whole earth.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſes </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p>Now in ſo much, That ſutable to this <hi>Houſe</hi> of God, <hi>behaviour</hi> is required; my firſt vſe is this.</p>
            <p>Laboure to be within this <hi>houſe.</hi> Do as <hi>David,</hi> pſal. 23. 5. <hi>I will dwell in it for ever.</hi> This is the <hi>Mother of us all.</hi> This muſt be to us as the <hi>Ark of Noah;</hi> not onely to be in it, <hi>but abide in it,</hi> ſee <hi>Joh. 15. 6. 7. I. Joh.</hi> 2. 19. Away with ſeparation needleſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt; IT is a good word of CYPRIAN, <hi>He that hath not the Church for his Mother, he hath not God for his Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we be Members of this <hi>Houſe,</hi> it ſhall be our beſt <hi>behaviour</hi> to <note place="margin">2. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> carry ſo as becomes the houſe wee are come off. Let us look out like <hi>veſſels of honour, fitted for the Maſters uſe.</hi> a peeviſh or a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>behaviour</hi> argues a <hi>veſſell of diſhonour.</hi> Remember that of <hi>pſ. 93. 5. Holineſſe becomes thy houſe O Lord!</hi> it is good word of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi> chap. 6. verſ. 11. <hi>Should ſuch a man as I flee?</hi> Should one inrolled in the King of heavens Family carry baſeſly, idlely, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſively? Remember <hi>who are without,</hi> Revel. 22. 15. &amp;c. If civill carriage bee much required and looked after in a great mans houſe; how much more is chriſtian and ſpirituall <hi>behaviour</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in this great Lords <hi>Houſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then in particular, Let each Member minde the welfare and <note place="margin">3. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> ſtanding of Gods houſe. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> being interrogated how this ſhould bee, Anſwered, <hi>Orando, juvando, condolendo, congaudendo;</hi> for which acts, ſee theſe ſcriptures <hi>pſal. 122. 9. 7. 8. 9. Amos, 6. 6. Rom. 12. 15. I. Cor. 12. 26. pſal. 42. 4. pſal.</hi> 27. 4. &amp;c. Our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104070:7"/> greateſt joy and glory ſhall be to contribute our talents hither, <hi>to repaire breaches, to reſtore paths to dwell in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then in ſpeciall, Let Miniſters looke to their <hi>behaviour</hi> in this houſe. No houſe requires ſo wiſe and faithfull <hi>ſervants</hi> as this <note place="margin">4. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</note> doth. Remember theſe paſſages, <hi>Matth. 25. 21. 23. Luk. 12. 42. I. Car.</hi> 4. 2. Were thou but a <hi>doore-keeper</hi> in Gods houſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thy talent to His praiſe and the Churches good. Marke <hi>Moſes,</hi> his commendation; <hi>That hee was faithfull in all the houſe of God as a ſervant, Heb</hi> 3. 2. Why was <hi>Jehojada</hi> ſo honourably buried? was it not becauſe, <hi>hee had done good in the houſe of the Lord,</hi> II. Chron. 24. 16. The greateſt <hi>Elegium</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation</hi> that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> could get of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Funerall was that, <hi>dying hee was more carefull of the Churches good, then of his Crown, Family or Poſterity</hi> O Remember both the parts of that <hi>promiſe</hi> and <hi>threatning</hi> ſet down, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 45. 46. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If Miniſters would give notice of good <hi>behaviour</hi> in Gods <note place="margin">5. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> houſe, then let them learne to <hi>behave</hi> themſelves wiſely in their owne houſes; as <hi>Paul</hi> inſinuateth <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 3. 4. O that wee could learne to be as <hi>David,</hi> who <hi>pſal.</hi> 101. 2. ſaieth, <hi>I will walk in my houſe, with a perfect heart:</hi> but not to follow <hi>Eli</hi> his example, <hi>I. Sam. 4. 13. His ſonnes made themſelves vile, and he reſtrained them not.</hi> This might be laid to many of our doors, a good <hi>father</hi> and a good <hi>paſtor</hi> are very comely.</p>
            <p>If we are to <hi>behave</hi> our ſelves ſutable to this <hi>houſe,</hi> then avoide <note place="margin">6. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> diviſive motions, or ſchiſmaticall behaviour, ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. If a Republicke, or Army, or a City, or the rulers of a Ship be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, the <hi>ſequel</hi> is ruine. <hi>Matchiavels</hi> rule was, <hi>divide et impera.</hi> Our Lord inſinuatetd this, <hi>Mark</hi> 3. 25. O ſad is that word of <hi>Micah,</hi> chap. 7. 7! Good was that <hi>ſaying</hi> of <hi>Gregor, Nazanz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, That we think, ſpeake, and do the ſame. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. one in judgement, and in affection alſo.</p>
            <p>Since our <hi>behaviour</hi> is ſo looked upon, as it correſponds and <note place="margin">7. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> keeps due proportion with this Metaphoricall houſe, the true viſible Church, then our <hi>behaviour</hi> muſt not bee to glory in the outward ſhew and pompe of a glorious <hi>Temple.</hi> I deny not, but of old, <hi>Altars</hi> were piouſly erected, the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> reared up, the <hi>Temple</hi> finiſhed, <hi>Synagogues</hi> built, <hi>Kirks</hi> and <hi>Cells</hi> continued as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104070:7"/> adminicles of divine worſhip in the publick meetings of the ſaints: yet when theſe meeting places become dennes of theeves, and cadges of uncleanneſſe, it is juſt with God, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front them, as he did <hi>Shilo,</hi> and the <hi>Temple,</hi> ſee <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. 4. 14. <note place="margin">8. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Here I cannot but meete with that ſophiſme of BELLARM. <hi>The Kirk is a houſe,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>and one houſe hath but one</hi> Rector, <hi>who can be this but</hi> Peter <hi>and his ſucceſſours?</hi> ANSW. 1. grant all this, what is it for the preſent Roman <hi>Biſhope?</hi> this is but beggerie. 2. Make <hi>Peter</hi> that one <hi>Rector</hi> (which is denyed by us) yet I deny that he is <hi>head</hi> or <hi>ſpouſe</hi> of the Church. 3. <hi>Cyprian</hi> makes a better vſe of that <hi>Rectorſhipe,</hi> who epiſt. 67. ſayes, <hi>We are many Pastors, yet we feed but one flock, which is the Lords.</hi> Epiſcopatus <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus eſt, cujus a ſingulis in ſolidum part tenetur;</hi> but of this more <note place="margin">
                  <hi>II. Title,</hi> Church of the Living GOD.</note> hereafter.</p>
            <p>Next followes the ſecond <hi>branch</hi> of his Commendatory, <hi>The Church of</hi> &amp;c. Where we are firſt to explicate this other <hi>Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> or <hi>denomination,</hi> then gives ſome uſes of our <hi>behaviour</hi> to the things ſo denominated.</p>
            <p>If any inquire here, what Church is meaned? I anſwere both <note place="margin">What Church is here mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?</note> the Catholick and each particular, the true Viſible and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, the Kirk Eſſentiall, and Organick, the Kirk Nationall, &amp; Domeſtick, the Antient and Moderne, the Orientall &amp; the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall, the Kirk more or leſſe pure. For each of theſe ſo long as they adhere to revealed <hi>trueths,</hi> and remaine joyned to the <note place="margin">Of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</note> 
               <hi>baſe,</hi> ſo farre they are <hi>The Churches of the living God,</hi> his <hi>body,</hi> his <hi>ſpouſe.</hi> Now what is added? This <hi>title</hi> is added, both for diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and for demonſtration; As to the firſt, This is to diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the <hi>Owner</hi> of the Kirk, 1. from that which never <hi>lived.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">I. For diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> 2. from that alſo, which though it was, or is living, yet it is but <hi>mortall.</hi> 3. yea from that alſo, which ſo liveth, as not ſubject to <hi>mortality,</hi> as the <hi>Devill:</hi> or as ſome learned <hi>Divines</hi> more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hold out thus. 1. There be <hi>dij deputati</hi> and <hi>reputati,</hi> as pſal. 82. 6. <hi>I have ſaid, yee are gods.</hi> 2. there be <hi>dij fictitij</hi> or <hi>manufacti,</hi> dead <hi>gods</hi> or <hi>Idols,</hi> pſal. 138. 15. &amp;c. 3. there be <hi>dij ſenſuales,</hi> as of theſe, <hi>whoſe god is their belly,</hi> phil. 3. 19. 4. there be <hi>dij uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pantes,</hi> as the <hi>devils,</hi> II. <hi>Cor. 4. 4. the god of this World:</hi> but none of theſe is the <hi>living GOD.</hi> It had been good for theſe, if they had never lived. This limitation is mainely in oppoſition to theſe falſe gods, whoſe <hi>pictures</hi> invented and framed by humane
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104070:8"/> braine, were adored and ſacrificed unto, in the heat hen Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; as if <hi>Paul</hi> upon this very account ſhould urge a reverend and holy behaviour in <hi>Timothy,</hi> becauſe he was an <hi>Office-bearer</hi> 
               <note place="margin">II. For demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration.</note> not in <hi>Diana's</hi> Temple, or in <hi>Jupiters</hi> Capitoll, nor in the houſe of <hi>Dagon</hi> or <hi>Bell,</hi> nor in the <hi>Synagogue</hi> of <hi>Satan,</hi> but in the Church of the <hi>Living GOD.</hi> Then, ſecondly, for demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is, what a <hi>living God</hi> this <hi>Owner</hi> is both formally and effectually, which Schoolmen well explain, when they ſay, <hi>That God is life quidditative, intellectuall, interminable, eternall, ſimple, immutable, incommunicable, infinite and perfect;</hi> grounding vpon theſe words, <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 6. 16. As alſo <hi>who gives life,</hi> 1. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall,</hi> as <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 28. then the <hi>rationall,</hi> as <hi>Gen. 1. 26. Jer. 38. 16. Pſal. 32. 8. Iſai. 28. 26. Pſal.</hi> 36. 9. then the <hi>ſupernaturall life,</hi> as when he is called <hi>our life,</hi> ſee <hi>Col. 3. 3. 4. Galat. 2. 20. I. Pet.</hi> 1. 23. both theſe are no leſſe well explained by <hi>Marianus Victorinꝰ,</hi> lib. 4. againſt the <hi>Arians;</hi> upon theſe words of <hi>Joh.</hi> chap. 1. 4. <hi>In him was life, and his life was the light of men. Vivere Dei non eſt quale noſtrum, ſed eſt vivere ſummum, primum, fontaneum, a ſemet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſo, eſt vivere ante omne vivere, ſui ſibi principium, omnium effecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum, viventium origo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Title</hi> thus explained. The 1. <hi>Obſerve</hi> may be this; Since <note place="margin">2. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes of this 1 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> the Church is the Church of the <hi>living God,</hi> then it is indefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctible, hence it is called, <hi>the City of the living God,</hi> Heb. 12. 22. this is from his gracious aſſiſting preſence, and if it were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then there might have been a time ſuppoſed, wherein no ſaving <hi>trueths</hi> ſhould be revealed on earth, but there was never ſuch a time, nor ſhall be. This our <hi>Mother</hi> never dieth.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Title</hi> is a great comfort to <hi>Believers,</hi> to <hi>living Members,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> even in the midſt of the greateſt and ſaddeſt Revolutions, in the time of their greateſt preſſures &amp; ſufferings; Mark to this, that of <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 19. 25. and of <hi>Pſal. 18. 46. The Lord liveth.</hi> And ſo much the more, if we ſuffer, <hi>becauſe we trust in the living GOD,</hi> I. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 10.</p>
            <p>Then beware to reproach the <hi>Living God.</hi> Let all <hi>Rabſhake's</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> and <hi>Golia's</hi> looke to themſelves, ſee <hi>I. Sam.</hi> 17. 36. and <hi>II. King.</hi> 19. 4. O that ſcoffers and deriders of the ſacred Trinitie, would take this to heart!</p>
            <p>Then whoſoever profeſſeth Memberſhip of the Church of <note place="margin">4 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> the <hi>Living God,</hi> Let them learne to <hi>live to him,</hi> Rom. 14. 7. 8. to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104070:8"/> this end, enter into this Kirk <hi>by a new and living way,</hi> Heb. 10. 20. Behave your ſelves as <hi>Children of the Living God,</hi> Rom. 9. 26. Carry as <hi>ſervants of the Living God,</hi> Dan. 6. 20. <hi>Thirſt for the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God,</hi> pſal. 42. 2. <hi>Offer your bodies a living ſacrifice,</hi> Rom. 12. 1. <hi>Truſt in the living God,</hi> I. <hi>Tim. 6. 17. Sweare by him that liveth,</hi> Ier. 4. 2. <hi>Fear the living God.</hi> Dan. 6. 26. then <hi>worſhip him that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for ever,</hi> Revel. 4. 9. Rev. 5. 14. Then take heed of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing from him, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 10, 31. If there be in us a Vitall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall that is indeed ſpirituall, then aſſuredly theſe foreſaid Vitall operations are apparent; elſe it may be ſaid of us, as of the Angel of <hi>Sardis,</hi> Revel. 3. 1. <hi>Thou hast a name that thou liveſt, but thou art dead.</hi> They that are ſealed with the ſeale of the <hi>Living God,</hi> will <note place="margin">5 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> yeeld fruits of holineſſe and happineſſe, <hi>Revel. 7. 2. II. Cor.</hi> 3. 3.</p>
            <p>Let this be in a ſpeciall way applyed to Miniſters, who are not <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts; That all their actings bee in a lively way, in the Lord, and for the Lord. A lifeleſſe Miniſtry, cold and careleſſe, is a ſoul-Murthering office. Farre be it from us in our Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall acquittalls, that popiſh tenet, <hi>Miſſa non mordet.</hi> It is marked of Chriſt, <hi>Matth. 7. 29. That he taught with Authority,</hi> and the happy iſſue of this is ſet down, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 5. which is well ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, <hi>The poorear evangelized,</hi> that is, drenched in it. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> preached to the Theſſalonians. <hi>I. Theſſ. 2. 3. Wee were bold in our God, to speake unto them the Gospell of God in much contention.</hi> and to the <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> chap. 1. 28. <hi>Wee teach every man in all wiſdome, that we may preſent &amp;c.</hi> And yet to cleare this, marke theſe two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table paſſages of <hi>Paul</hi> in his powerfull preaching, to draw men from vanities and idols to the <hi>Living God,</hi> ſee <hi>I. Theſſ. 1. 9. For they themſelves ſhew what manner of entring in we had unto you, and how yee returned to God from your idols, to ſerve the true and living God.</hi> and that other, to this purpoſe; <hi>Act. 14. 15. Sirs, we preach unto you, that yee ſhould turne from theſe vanities, unto the living God.</hi> So ſhould wee now be moſt ſedulous to root out in ſpeciall, the imbred ſeeds of <hi>Popery,</hi> in each of us by nature. And yet further, that our <hi>behaviour</hi> may be ſutable to the church of the <hi>living God,</hi> Marke that worthy <hi>Apeale</hi> of PAUL, as to this, <hi>I. Theſſ. 2. 10. Ye are witneſſes and God alſo, how holily, and juſtly and unblameably wee behaved our ſelves among you that beleeve, &amp;c.</hi> Here are three good <hi>Adverbs. 1. How holily,</hi> a Miniſter ſhould be <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord,</hi> indued with perſonal-holines, profeſſion-holines, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104070:9"/> in his Family, and holines Vocationall, this is moſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite. Sad was that ſpeech of a worthy <hi>hearer</hi> upon a graceleſſe PREACHER. <hi>When hee is out of the Pulpit, I wiſh he never came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into it, he is ſo profane: but when he is in the pulpit, I wiſh that he never came out of it, he preaches ſo to the life to others.</hi> Then, <hi>how justly,</hi> that is, wronging no mans <hi>interest,</hi> giving to each in Gods family his <hi>portion</hi> in due ſeaſon, revealing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God,</hi> applying in a wiſe way, <hi>Law-threats</hi> and <hi>Gospel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> giving both <hi>aloes</hi> and <hi>cordials, bitter</hi> &amp; <hi>ſweet</hi> as PATIENTS ſtand in need of it. Thirdly, <hi>how unblameably,</hi> PETER very well urges upon all, <hi>an holy and honeſt converſation,</hi> I. Pet. 1. 15. I. Pet. 2. 12. O how much more is this required in a Miniſter; which moves <hi>Paul,</hi> I. Tim. 4. 12. to deſire TIMOTHY <hi>to be a paterne to believers, in word, in purity, in faith, in ſpirit, in charity, in converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> our <hi>example</hi> being more viewed then our <hi>precepts;</hi> which puts me in minde, of a ſad ſpeech of <hi>Martianus</hi> Biſhope of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople,</hi> recorded by <hi>Socrates,</hi> lib. 5. chap. 20. <hi>Haſt. eccl.</hi> and it is this, After that he had ordained one <hi>Sabatius</hi> to be a <hi>Preſbyter</hi> in PONTUS, and finding him afterward to judaize, to turne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious and turbulent, and foſtring the ſchiſme of the <hi>quartadeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani,</hi> he did burſt forth in theſe ſad expreſſions: <hi>Would to the Lord, that I had laid my hands on briars and thornes, that day, I gave thee impoſition of hands, thy carriage is ſo full of blame.</hi> I end with this humble <hi>Requeſt.</hi> Let us all indeavour for ſuch <hi>behaviour</hi> as is ſutable to <hi>revealed trueths,</hi> as is ſutable to the <hi>power of godlineſſe,</hi> as is ſutable to theſe <hi>Ordinances</hi> we hold out to others, and as is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to our <hi>holy profeſſion.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>III Title.</hi> The Pillar of trueth.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now followes the laſt two <hi>titles</hi> of that place, where <hi>Timothy</hi> his <hi>behaviour</hi> muſt bee <hi>The pillar and ground of the trueth.</hi> Now of this are three different <hi>references.</hi> 1. Some referre them to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> as if he were <hi>the ground and pillar of the trueth.</hi> thus <hi>Leigh.</hi> and <hi>Chillingsworth.</hi> apply theſe titles, for ſo ſay they, was <hi>Attains</hi> called by <hi>Euſeb.</hi> lib. chap. 1. for his conſtant <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> but this is not right. For this is the <hi>predicate</hi> of the Church here, and one is not a Church. 2. Some referre and joine theſe words to the ſubſequent, verſ. 16. theſe materiall trueths being a <hi>Pillar,</hi> ſo <hi>Camero,</hi> ſo <hi>Heinſius,</hi> ſo alſo <hi>Mareſ.</hi> t. 1. <hi>Contr.</hi> 5. contra <hi>Tirin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> p. 163. 3. Moſt of the ſoundeſt <hi>Interpreters</hi> referre this to the <hi>Antecedent,</hi> for which cauſe, the originall Greeke hath it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104070:9"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even referring to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo is the like <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 16. It is the Church to which theſe two <hi>denominations</hi> belong.</p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt ſpeak of this <hi>Pillar of trueth</hi> attributed to the <hi>Church.</hi> II. of this <hi>ground of trueth,</hi> why, and how it is thus called. As for the firſt, I propoſe theſe. 1. What Church it is, that is this <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</hi> 2. Why the Church is ſo called. 3. I ſhall vindicate the place from foule <hi>aſperſions,</hi> and falſe <hi>gloſſes</hi> put upon it. Then 4. I ſhall raiſe ſome <hi>obſerves,</hi> and give ſome <hi>vſes</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, to make the point more cleare, marke ſhortly <note place="margin">I. The vſe of Pillars. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5.</note> and in <hi>generall,</hi> for what vſes <hi>Pillars</hi> are reared up. Wee reade in <hi>ſcripture,</hi> That they have been erected for <hi>witneſſing,</hi> ſo <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. 13. 52. 2. For a <hi>Memoriall,</hi> ſo was <hi>Abſoloms</hi> pillar for preſerving his memorie alive, II. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 18. 3. <hi>Pillars</hi> are erected as an <hi>Embleme</hi> of a judgement, ſo <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. 26. 4. For <hi>Strengthning</hi> and <hi>ſupporting</hi> great buildings, ſo <hi>Judg.</hi> 16. 29. 5. Wee reade <hi>I. king.</hi> 7. 21. that <hi>Solomon</hi> erected two <hi>pillars</hi> in the Temple porch, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Jachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz,</hi> interpreted by the ſeventy <hi>Interp.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>Direction</hi> and <hi>Protection:</hi> or as others, <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Integrity;</hi> They were as the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and the <hi>Thummim.</hi> purity of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and ſanctity of <hi>life,</hi> a ſound <hi>faith</hi> and pure <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> a ſound <hi>head,</hi> and charitable <hi>hands,</hi> ſound <hi>precepts</hi> &amp; good <note place="margin">6.</note> 
               <hi>practiſe,</hi> by the which God directeth &amp; eſtabliſheth his Church. 6. Amongſt the <hi>Romans</hi> were <hi>Pillars</hi> erected to <hi>Conquerours,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter warres for Triumph, ſo in <hi>Foro</hi> there were new <hi>Obelisks,</hi> and in <hi>Campo Martio,</hi> ſuch <hi>pillars</hi> and high <hi>statues.</hi> But the <hi>pillar</hi> 
               <note place="margin">7.</note> here mentioned, is not a <hi>Materiall</hi> but <hi>a Metaphoricall,</hi> not a <hi>reall,</hi> but a <hi>figurative,</hi> not an <hi>Architectonicall,</hi> but <hi>Politicall,</hi> not <hi>ſimply</hi> but <hi>comparatively</hi> ſo, that is, in reſpect of men locking &amp; leaning to it.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>queſtion</hi> firſt to bee anſwered, to wit, What is the <note place="margin">2ly, What Church is this pillar?</note> Church that is this <hi>Pillar?</hi> I Anſ. firſt in <hi>generall.</hi> 1. Each true Church is this <hi>Pillar,</hi> yea each individuall <hi>Believer</hi> is a pillar in a ſound ſenſe, as <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 12. But, ſecondly, If the <hi>Quaere</hi> bee, to which this <hi>attribution</hi> chiefly and primarly belongs, that is, whether firſtly to the Catholick, or to the particular Churches? Then I anſwere thus. That ſince the Catholick Church is firſt in <hi>Divine Intention,</hi> and in <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> and in <hi>Priviledges,</hi> and in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> and ſo in <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>Perfection:</hi> yea and ſince the <hi>Fede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Promiſes</hi> are firſt made to the Church Catholick, as is well
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104070:10"/> proven by <hi>J. Hudſon;</hi> Hence it is, that I affirme, that the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> the <hi>denomination,</hi> the <hi>qualifications</hi> of a pillar, do all belong primarly to the Church Catholick. It is well ſaid of <hi>Jerome,</hi> even to this very point, <hi>Orbis major eſt urbe.</hi> This is a cleare trueth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>affection</hi> applicable, or rightly applyed to the Catholick, is not ſtraight and ſtill to be applyed to each particular as to be infallible, or to be <hi>The Mother of us all;</hi> it were incompetent to apply this to each particular, though both theſe, in <hi>act</hi> not er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, are this <hi>Pillar,</hi> yet with more and leſſe, yet with ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, yet as of the higher and of the lower degree: Which I the rather inſiſt upon, to refute that new conceit of <hi>Independents,</hi> who hold no kirk to be a <hi>Pillar of truth,</hi> but their <hi>particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations;</hi> This is juſt as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, <hi>No true kirk but that of Rome:</hi> and as the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> before them ſaid, <hi>No true kirk but in Africa.</hi> but both are miſtaken, not knowing the true <hi>affections</hi> of <note place="margin">II. Why, to be a pillar, is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the church.</note> the true Catholick Viſible Church.</p>
            <p>Now to cleare the ſecond, That is, Why this <hi>Title</hi> is given to the Church. I ſhall firſt <hi>negativè</hi> ſhew in what ſenſe, the Church is not a <hi>Pillar,</hi> then <hi>poſitive</hi> ſhew in what ſenſe, it is a <hi>Pillar.</hi> As to the firſt, that is well cleared by <hi>D. Feeld,</hi> lib. 4. cap. 4, of the Church. 1. IT is not the <hi>Pillar of trueth,</hi> as if divine <hi>trueths</hi> for their entitie and beeing, did depend on the Church: nay ſayes <note place="margin">1. In what ſenſe, it is not the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of truth.</note> CHRYSOST. well. <hi>The Church depends on theſe trueths.</hi> 2. Nor is it a <hi>Pillar,</hi> as if our <hi>faith</hi> depended on Church-Authority. To which purpoſe, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſayes well, lib. 3. cap. 1. <hi>Inst.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick writes are the <hi>Pillars</hi> of our <hi>faith,</hi> and cap. 2. the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is the <hi>Pillar of trueth,</hi> and not mens <hi>Authority.</hi> The Church is not the authour or procreant cauſe of our <hi>faith.</hi> 3. Nor is the Church a <hi>Pillar,</hi> as if God could no other wayes reveale <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall trueths,</hi> but by its Miniſtry, as by neceſſity invincible; No, Theſe have been revealed both by Himſelfe immediatly to this or that private man, and by Angels. 4. Nor is it, as if the Kirk were in no ſenſe ſubject to <hi>ignorance</hi> or the leaſt <hi>errour,</hi> in its deciſions, and ſo to appeale to it, as the ſupreame infallible <hi>Judge,</hi> to whoſe diſcretion appertaineth the differencing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <note place="margin">2. In what ſenſe, it is the pillar of trueth.</note> 
               <hi>trueth</hi> and <hi>falſehood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I affirme the Church to be a <hi>Pillar of trueth,</hi> with <hi>Calvin, Beza, Davenant. Chamier,</hi> &amp;c. 1. As <hi>Cuſtos,</hi> it is a keeper, to which divine ſaving, needfull revealed <hi>trueths</hi> are concredited.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104070:10"/> To which purpoſe heare, what theſe three Fathers ſay to this point. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> lib. 3. cap. 4. <hi>The Apoſtles laid up in the Church, as in a rich treaſure all trueth, and ſhe keeps the Apoſtles faith &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</hi> Tertullian. <hi>The Kirk keeps the ſcriptures, which are Chriſts heirſhip.</hi> Lactant. lib. 6 Inſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The Catholick Church onely keeps the true worſhip of God, it onely is the fountaine of trueth, if any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into it, or go out of it, he is a ſtranger to ſalvation; without are errours, fancies and lies.</hi> 2. As <hi>Tutana,</hi> as a defendreſſe, that is, ſupporting and maintaining it, as CHRYSOST. Hom. 11. on <hi>Tim.</hi> explicats this well, when he ſayes, <hi>The Kirk by its Miniſtry and preaching, ſupports and upholds the trueth as it were, on its ſhoulders.</hi> 3. As PR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>CO, as an <hi>Herauld,</hi> proclaiming, promulgating, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing it, and bearing witneſſe to it, which no ſociety on earth doth or can do, but the Church. 4. As REGISTRATRIX, a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder,</hi> tranſmitting it to poſterity ſucceſſively, ſo it is a <hi>Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> a <hi>Tutrix,</hi> an <hi>Herauld,</hi> a <hi>Notar,</hi> keeping, defending, proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, recording divine trueths, which moved <hi>Ravanella</hi> rightly to ſay, That <hi>In Eccleſia prostant Veritates Catholicae.</hi> And as <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaid before him, lib 3. cap. 6. contra DONAT. <hi>Every Kirk ſhould leade men to the faith.</hi> But yet to make the juſtneſſe of this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication</hi> more cleare. I ſay, That as of old, the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and in ordinary, <hi>Magiſtrats</hi> now, erect <hi>Pillars</hi> &amp; <hi>posts,</hi> to the which they affixe their <hi>Edicts, Lawes</hi> &amp; <hi>Wills:</hi> or to which of old, were joined their <hi>Tabulae penſiles,</hi> in the which, <hi>Proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations</hi> carrying their minds, are expreſſed, notified and inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo the Kirk to <hi>Written Trueths,</hi> it is not they, but it demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats them: even as the <hi>Pillars</hi> or <hi>broads</hi> affixed to them, are not the LAW'S <hi>in recto,</hi> ſo it is with the Kirk, according to that <hi>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the ſame CHRYSOST. <hi>Trueth eſtabliſheth the Kirk, and not the Kirk the Trueth.</hi> HAMMOND in his <hi>Notes</hi> to this, well explains this. <hi>The vſefulneſſe of a</hi> pillar <hi>is from the</hi> baſis, <hi>on which it ſtands, elſe it will down. If the</hi> baſis <hi>be ſo ſet that it ſinke not, the</hi> pillar <hi>being firmely faſtened on it, and ſtanding upright, it is able to beare a vast weight of building upon it, and ſo theſe two, though ſeverall in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, (as contiguous not continuat) yet joining together, and ſo, as it were conſolidated together in one, they do as one not ſeverally ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port what is laid on it; ſo that as ſaid is,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>one here is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by two, that is, the</hi> pillar <hi>upon the</hi> baſe <hi>firmely ſustaining that, which is built and erected upon it, ſo the Church firmely built upon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104070:11"/> the</hi> baſis <hi>of trueths (to the which the body of divine trueths are delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) holds them out to her Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since the <hi>Trent</hi> Papiſts, the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> and other <hi>Ieſuits</hi> pervere <note place="margin">3 The due vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of this place from the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits cavills</note> this place, I wipe off their <hi>Objections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Say they. If the Church be the <hi>pillar of trueth,</hi> but in the ſenſe now delivered, then it is rather a <hi>Chiſt</hi> unto <hi>Trueth,</hi> and not the <hi>Pillar</hi> of it, thus it is but as a Book-ſellers <hi>Shope,</hi> containing many <hi>Trueths</hi> in it. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Church is both, that is, both an <hi>Ark,</hi> wherein are the <hi>Tables</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> as alſo a <hi>Pillar</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Ob.</note> in the ſenſe given; theſe are well conſiſting. 2. The Church acts that which no <hi>Chiſt</hi> or Book-ſellers <hi>Shope</hi> can do, it not onely keeps, but it promulgats &amp; tranſmitts the <hi>truth</hi> to ages. 3. The Church is not onely <hi>Index,</hi> but alſo a <hi>Vindex</hi> of the trueth, yea in a ſound ſenſe, it is alſo a <hi>Judex</hi> of it, to wit, ſecundarie, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall, and accountable. Well doth <hi>Altingius</hi> L. C. p. 2. pag. 588. diſtinguiſh. <hi>The Church is a pillar not in regarde of inherent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibilitie in every thing; but in respect of its office adhering to it. that is, keeping, diſcerning, interpreting, preaching the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</hi> Here the Ieſuite <hi>Becan.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 3. of his <hi>Man,</hi> aſſumes, then even ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our ſenſe, <hi>The Roman Kirk is a true kirk, becauſe it acts all the wayes wee allow to a pillar.</hi> Here I deny the <hi>Antecedent,</hi> it ſmothers and oppoſes <hi>revealed trueths,</hi> as ſhall be proven. Then when he arguments thus, whatſoever Church acts theſe foure wayes now ſet down, that is a true <hi>Viſible Church,</hi> but the <hi>Roman kirk</hi> acts thus. Here againe I grant the <hi>propoſition,</hi> and deny the <hi>aſſumption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellar.</hi> lib. de eccl. Milit. cap. 12. 13. reaſons thus, <hi>The Pillar</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Ob.</note> 
               <hi>of trueth is infallible, but the Viſible Kirk is the Pillar of trueth,</hi> ergo <hi>it is infallible.</hi> Anſw. I may grant both the <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> &amp; with no diſadvantage to our <hi>Cauſe.</hi> 2. In the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> ſenſe, I deny them both. 3. Whether I grant or deny both, yet the Elench is not inferred. What is this to the Roman kirk, where at they aime in this diſpute? But <hi>Bellarm,</hi> indeavours to ſtrengthen his <hi>inference</hi> thus. 1. Upon this ground onely, and no other, was the Roman kirk called the <hi>Mother and Miſtreſſe of all Churches,</hi> that it is and was the <hi>Pillar of trueth.</hi> Whence alſo it was that <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writting of this place, hath theſe words, <hi>Though all the World be Gods, yet the Church onely is his Houſe and pillar, whereof</hi> Damaſus Biſhope <hi>of Rome is Rector this day.</hi> Hence it is, ſayes he,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104070:11"/> that the <hi>Roman</hi> kirk, was ſo eſteemed, for the emitting &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting infallible <hi>trueths</hi> to all Chriſtian Churches. Now to all this I might anſwere, as <hi>Iſaias.</hi> chap. 33. 23. ſaid of the Aſſyrian forces. <hi>Thy tacklings are looſed, they could not well ſtrengthen their maſt.</hi> Yet in particular I anſwere 1. to argue from <hi>Rome</hi> now <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaticall,</hi> to what it was, when <hi>Apoſtolicall,</hi> is very inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. 2. It was not ſo ſtiled by any antient <hi>Writter</hi> of the firſt 600 years: for then was no ſupremacy over other Churches, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it and other Churches were ſiſterly aſſociated &amp; collaterall, then it was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended, as <hi>Solidata ſuper Petram,</hi> which <hi>Rock</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Cyprian, Hieron, Auguſt.</hi> &amp; others is <hi>Christ.</hi> 3. It is, flate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denied, That the kirk of <hi>Rome</hi> emitts <hi>all ſaving trueths</hi> though it retain ſome <hi>trueths,</hi> if hee except, then it is a true Church in ſo far as it retains ſome <hi>trueths,</hi> even wee being <hi>Judges,</hi> and in ſo farre, is a <hi>Pillar.</hi> I Anſ. 1. Be it ſo: but as we ſay of a <hi>man,</hi> he may be a man <hi>eſſentially,</hi> as conſiſting of two eſſentiall parts, <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>body;</hi> who yet is not ſo, for the trueth of <hi>integrity,</hi> if there bee either exceſſe or defect, maimed or monſtruous: and for the trueth of <hi>Perfection,</hi> he may yet be farre leſſe a <hi>man,</hi> as if a <hi>Foole,</hi> if <hi>witleſſe,</hi> if <hi>mad;</hi> ſo I ſay of the preſent Roman Church, or as our <hi>Divines</hi> diſtinguiſh. A <hi>Man</hi> may be a true man <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſically,</hi> as for <hi>entitie,</hi> who is not ſo <hi>morally,</hi> that is, for <hi>honeſty.</hi> As we ſay of a <hi>Theefe,</hi> he is truly a man for <hi>eſſence,</hi> though he be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a true man, for <hi>fidelity.</hi> ſo the Roman kirk is a true kirk <hi>equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally,</hi> being for parts <hi>integrall,</hi> and for <hi>perfection,</hi> a moſt falſe Kirk. 4. As to that paſſage of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the very flattering <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts,</hi> with their <hi>Dominus deus noſter Papa, Chriſtus noſter, ſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor noſtor Papa,</hi> do confeſſe theſe <hi>Commentaries</hi> to be ſpurious, and not to be <hi>Ambroſes</hi> at all: but granting them to be his, yet, as is well marked both by <hi>Feeld</hi> and <hi>Cartwright,</hi> they are thus to bee read, whereof <hi>Damaſus is a Ruler,</hi> but not <hi>the Ruler;</hi> for ſo are all <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Paſtors</hi> as <hi>Cyprian</hi> well ſayes, there is one <hi>Biſhope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> wherof each hath a part. But what a <hi>Rector</hi> even this <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> was, the bloody <hi>Conteſts</hi> between him &amp; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſacius,</hi> about that <hi>Idoll</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Chayre</hi> &amp; the <hi>Supremacy</hi> hiſtorians do teſtifie. <note place="margin">4. Some obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and vſes. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now ere I come to the laſt <hi>title.</hi> Anent this, That the Church of the <hi>Living God,</hi> is the <hi>Pillar of the trueth;</hi> I obſerve 1. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Society</hi> it is, that either expresſly or by juſt conſequence, oppoſeth <hi>revealed trueths,</hi> that is not the <hi>Pillar of trueth:</hi> whence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104070:12"/> I inferre, That the Roman kirk cannot be this <hi>Pillar of trueth,</hi> ſince it enerrats <hi>divine trueths,</hi> what by addition, what by detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Hieron.</hi> hath a trimme ſpeech, when he ſayes, <hi>Sanctorum Congregatio eſt dicta columna, &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>The company of ſaints is called a</hi> pillar <hi>both for ſoliditie and for stabilitie.</hi> and Theodoret. <hi>The company of Believers is called the</hi> pillar of trueth, <hi>becauſe being grounded on the Rock, they remaine ſtable &amp; unmoveable, &amp; ſo preach dogmatick trueths.</hi> But ſo it is, the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of the Roman Kirk doth not hold out infallibly, <hi>divine revealed trueths,</hi> as <hi>Tiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> would have it. Our learned <hi>Divines</hi> have much holden out the trueth of this <hi>negative,</hi> by the induction of the chiefe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars; as anent the <hi>Mediation</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>Juſtification, Free-will,</hi> number and efficacy of <hi>Sacraments, Traditions,</hi> equalled if not preferred to <hi>Scripture,</hi> the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Notes</hi> of the Scriptures. All which Doctrinalls of <hi>faith</hi> are by them fearfully depraved. Wherefore paſſing theſe; I offer to hold the point out meerlie in theſe two <hi>heads</hi> at this time. 1. Let any conſider the <hi>XII Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of the new <hi>Tridentine Faith,</hi> approven by <hi>Pius</hi> IV. P. called the new <hi>Symbol,</hi> &amp; now dayly urged by the Spayniſh <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> wherein are ſo groſſe <hi>additions</hi> ſupperadded to that wee finde in <hi>Scripture,</hi> or which wee call the Apoſtles <hi>Creed,</hi> that any <hi>Reader</hi> that compares, ſhall eaſily finde them, as is well both obſerved by <hi>Crakenthorp, H. Lynd,</hi> and <hi>L. Sharpus.</hi> 2. Let any impartiall <hi>Reader</hi> conſider the <hi>five Propoſitiones,</hi> called the determination of <hi>Innoc.</hi> X. anno 1653. for the <hi>Moliniſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> and he ſhall finde in them a new <hi>faith,</hi> unknown to the better and purertimes of the Church. Certaine it is, a <hi>heterodox Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> can no more lay challenge to a <hi>Pillar,</hi> then a <hi>Where</hi> to <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity,</hi> or as a <hi>Theefe</hi> to <hi>honeſty.</hi> Whence it is acutly ſaid by one, of One thraſonickly boaſting, but miſapplying the words of <hi>Pſal. 75. 3. I beare up the Pillars of it.</hi> nay rather, as it is. <hi>II. King. 25. 13. They have broken the Pillars of braſſe, and carried the braſſe to Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Church of the <hi>Living God</hi> be a <hi>Pillar of trueth,</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">2 Obſ.</note> them out, then men may reade, and heare, and ſee theſe <hi>trueths;</hi> then it a Viſible Church and Pillar. Here I do lay aſide and juſtly condemne both <hi>extreams.</hi> 1. Is of theſe that mantain no Kirk to bee a true PILLAR, but that of the predeſtinate which is Inviſible. 2. Is of theſe, who hold no Kirk to be the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104070:12"/> 
               <hi>Pillar of trueth</hi> on earth, but a glorious, conſpicuous, viſible, pompatick, a Kirk dreſſed to the eye: full of worldly ſplendor, and outward magnificence, as <hi>Bellarm.</hi> defines it.</p>
            <p>If the Kirk of God be the <hi>Pillar of trueth,</hi> then that is a falſe aſſertion of the <hi>Socinian</hi> or <hi>Racovian</hi> Catechiſme; <hi>That from the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 Obſ.</note> 
               <hi>Apoſtles dayes, for the space of 1400 years, the Kirk of Christ hath periſhed, and that, in that whole long intervall, there was nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men called Chriſtians, but the Antichriſtian Whore, no ſaints then, no Pillars of trueth then.</hi> O this is moſt falſe and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, oppoſing the <hi>Promiſes</hi> made to the Church, <hi>againſt which the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile. Againſt which no weapon formed ſhall prosper,</hi> Iſai. 54. 17. ſee Iſai. 59. 21. Matth. 28. 20. A <hi>Pillar</hi> by ſtrong oppoſition may be made to ſhake and tremble, yea to be at a loſſe in its former ſtrength &amp; ſtanding: and yet it is not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cut off or removed from its baſe. <hi>Concuti poteſt, at non perire,</hi> the firmneſſe of it continues, when the outward ſplendor is not ſo apparent, but obſcured.</p>
            <p>Then it becomes all honeſt Miniſters to be as <hi>Pillars</hi> and <hi>poſts</hi> in Gods houſe, to hold out all <hi>revealed trueths</hi> in Gods houſe <note place="margin">4 Obſ. an vſe.</note> plainly, pertinently, powerfully. <hi>Malach. 2. 7. The Prieſts lips ſhould keep knowledge,</hi> that is, as one noteth, <hi>Even as his heart and braine is for himſelf, ſo ſhould his lips and tongue be for the good of the Kirk.</hi> Marke to that end, theſe two words of PAUL, <hi>Tit. 1. 9. Holding faſt the forme of ſound words.</hi> Phil. 2. 16. <hi>holding forth the word of life.</hi> The Lord ſayes to <hi>Jerem.</hi> chap. 1. 18. <hi>I have made thee this day an iron pillar.</hi> that is, firme, ſtrong, and ſtraight, ſo ſhould Miniſters be, and not <hi>broken Reeds, like Egypt</hi> Iſai. 36. 6. <hi>on which if a man lean, it will pierce his hand.</hi> It is a good <hi>remarke</hi> of <hi>Ravanella,</hi> This ſpeech of PAUL to <hi>Timothy</hi> is ſet down, not ſo much <hi>aſſertivè</hi> as <hi>preceptivè,</hi> what <hi>ought to bee, quomodo oporteat,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theſe that ſeeme to be <hi>pillars,</hi> ought ſo to carry, as that they may be real <hi>pillars.</hi> Let us do our duty in doing, in ſuffering, within the compaſſe of our <hi>Callings,</hi> remembring that ſweet word of Chriſt, <hi>Revel. 3. 12. Him that overcometh, will I make a pillar in the Temple of my God, and hee ſhall no more go out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we may ſee the great dignity of the Miniſtry; Wee are <note place="margin">5 Obſ.</note> intruſted with this <hi>depoſitum,</hi> this pearle of pryce, wee are the <hi>pillars</hi> to which are affixed the <hi>Oracles of God.</hi> See <hi>II. Cor. 4. 7. Wee have this treaſure &amp;c.</hi> and this to purpoſe, to propagate, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104070:13"/> preach to the World. It is well anſwered by <hi>Mareſ.</hi> to <hi>Tirin.</hi> Our <hi>aſſervation</hi> of divine trueths, is not as that of a <hi>Chiſt,</hi> locall and materiall, but as ſaid is, it is morall and formall; for to act as ſaid is, is not <hi>thecae</hi> ſed <hi>columnae.</hi> Let us then conſtantly attend at the <hi>poſts of Wiſdome</hi> which thus honours us, as to be <hi>pillars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since PAUL urges his good <hi>Behaviour</hi> in his particular <hi>Charge</hi> 
               <note place="margin">6 Obſ.</note> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> hence I collect that a particular Church joined to &amp; conſolidated, as it were, with the <hi>baſe,</hi> may well be called the <hi>Pillar of trueth;</hi> but if any ſuch particular adhere not to the <hi>baſe,</hi> it is no longer a <hi>Pillar.</hi> What are the ſeven Churches of the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer <hi>Aſia</hi> now? even turned to rubbiſh; What ar the famoꝰ <hi>Churchs</hi> of <hi>Africa</hi> now? Stables to impure <hi>Mahumetiſme.</hi> What is become of the renowned Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> the greater? Dennes of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity. What is become of many the celebrious Churches of <hi>Greece?</hi> Infected with pernitious hereſies. God is not tyed to particular times and places. As there was a famous orthodox <hi>Nicen Councell,</hi> ſo was there as infamous and unſound a <hi>Nicen.</hi> As there was an orthodox <hi>Epheſine Councell,</hi> ſo after, there was a wicked and a praedatorie <hi>Epheſin.</hi> O then it were good for all and every particular Church to remember to practiſe what the Spirit ſpeaketh to the Churches of <hi>Aſia.</hi> As to that of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> Rev. 2. 25. <hi>But that which ye have already hold faſt, till I come.</hi> As to that of <hi>Sardis,</hi> Revel. 3. 3. <hi>Remember therefore how thou hast received and heard, and hold faſt.</hi> As to that of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Rev. 2. 5. <hi>Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do thy firſt works.</hi> As to that of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> Revel. 3. 11. <hi>Hold that faſt which thou hast, that no man take thy Crown.</hi> As that of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea,</hi> Revel. 3. 18. <hi>I counſell thee to buy of me gold tried in the ſire, that thou mayeſt be rich, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this <hi>Pillar</hi> hold out this <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Rule,</hi> Then all that are within the verge and reach of it, ſhould looke to it, <note place="margin">7 Obſ,</note> walk by it, as it is ſaid of the <hi>braſen Serpent,</hi> Numb. 21. 9. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 14. ſo of this <hi>Pillar,</hi> looke to it, beleeve it, obey it, ſo farre as it followes Chriſt, <hi>I. cor.</hi> 11. 1. IT is marked of that <hi>Pillar</hi> that lead the <hi>Iſraelits,</hi> that it was one and the ſame pillar that was light to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but darkneſſe to <hi>Egypt,</hi> Exod. 14. 19. ſo the ſame <hi>Word</hi> preached by faithfull Paſtors, becomes to ſome <hi>The ſavour of life to life, to others of death unto death.</hi> II. Cor. 2. 16. as an <hi>Edict</hi> on the <hi>poſt,</hi> to ſome is matter of comfort, to others not ſo.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104070:13"/>
            <p>Here wee ſee clearly, That one and the ſame thing may bee both ſupporting and ſupported, both active and paſſive as to its <hi>being</hi> and <hi>vſe,</hi> and as to <hi>trueths.</hi> the Church ſupports the <hi>trueth,</hi> in the wayes before ſpecified, <hi>quoad declarari, ac manifestari. Trueth</hi> againe ſupports the Kirk, <hi>in genere entis et moris,</hi> that it hath the <hi>beeing</hi> of the Church of the <hi>Living GOD,</hi> and that it, in its Latitude and Complexe, ſhould be invincible and infallible. IT is not miſapplyed that of <hi>Prov. 9. 1. Wiſdome hath built her houſe, ſhe hath hewen out her ſeven pillars, &amp;c.</hi> But of this enough. Now I come to the greateſt and laſt <hi>title</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ground of the Trueth.</hi> Now I am to treate of the Church, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>IV Title.</hi> The ground of the truth.</note> under this <hi>notion;</hi> and becauſe this is moſt materiall, I muſt inſiſt a little on it. And the rather, in that the <hi>Moderne Jeſuits</hi> affirme that wee <hi>Proteſtants</hi> abhorre to reade this, and that this TEXT is ſo pungent, that wee flee from the literall <hi>ſenſe</hi> of it. Therefore this ſhall be my <hi>Method.</hi> Firſt, I am to cleare the words of this <hi>Title.</hi> II. To propoſe that grand <hi>queſtion,</hi> that falls pertinently <note place="margin">1. The <hi>Title</hi> is explained.</note> here to bee diſcuſſed, which is; <hi>Whether this ground can make a ground or grounds?</hi> III. I muſt cleare ſome other <hi>doubts</hi> propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed here, &amp; that by way of vindication. Then IV. Some <hi>vſes</hi> to be made of this <hi>aſſertion;</hi> That Gods Kirk is the <hi>ground of the trueth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt. The greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by ſome is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>Fundamentum,</hi> by others better <hi>Firmamentum</hi> in latine. As <hi>Whitak.</hi> Contr. 4. q. 5. <hi>Criticks</hi> diſtinguiſh between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> thus, That the firſt is properly rendered, a <hi>ground,</hi> the ſecond, properly a <hi>ſeat,</hi> applying the word, <hi>ground,</hi> to the <hi>trueths</hi> exiſting and revealed; and applying the word <hi>ſeat,</hi> to the Church; according to what wee reade <hi>Matth. 22. 2. of Moſes Chayre or ſeat.</hi> Of the which Criticiſme, <hi>P. Bayne</hi> gives this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in Comment, on <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 19. 20. <hi>That which ſo ſupports all; as that it is not ſupported,</hi> in a right and ſtrict notion is a <hi>ground,</hi> ſo <hi>Maimonides</hi> call his booke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>but that which ſo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The ground of grounds.</note> 
               <hi>ſupports, as that it is ſupported,</hi> is properly a <hi>ſeat</hi> and <hi>receptacle</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but improperly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or a <hi>ground.</hi> Yet wee ſhall vſe it, as it is here in the Engliſh rendered. <hi>Theophylact. Beda, P. de Aliaco, Chaloner,</hi> explicate this TITLE thus; <hi>The Church is the ground of trueth, becauſe ſupernaturall divine trueths are in it, we lean to the Church, as to the ſeat of trueth, but not to it; as to the loweſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104070:14"/> and chiefest ground, why theſe trueths are trueths.</hi> D. F. Whyte 3. Conf. p. 4. clears this well thus. <hi>The pure Apoſtolick Church was the</hi> pillar <hi>and</hi> ground of trueth <hi>ſimply, intierly &amp; fully in all things, but the ſubſequent and the Moderne Churches, is onely ſo with limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is, conditionally, that is, in ſo farre as they deliver Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick doctrines, the Apostles were exempted in all their deciſions from all errours: but the Fathers and Councels are onely ſo, in ſo farre, as they adhere to the trueths written by Prophets and Apoſtles.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed what hee ſayes, is all granted by the more moderate PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PISTS, as by <hi>Occam, Cuſanus Picus, Gerſon.</hi> IT was the old do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <note place="margin">Ground 1. Perſonall. 2. Doctrinall 3. Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</note> of CHRYSOST. Homil. 49. on Matth. <hi>Let no man beleeve Churches, but in ſo farre as they lean to the Scriptures, if thou wouldſt know where is the true Church, then flee and run to the Scriptures.</hi> But yet further to cleare this, NOTE, as <hi>Davenant</hi> well obſerves, That there is a threefold <hi>ground of trueth.</hi> 1. Is <hi>Perſonall,</hi> and that is Chriſt, <hi>I. Cor. 3. 11. Iſai.</hi> 28. 16. 2. Is <hi>doctrinall,</hi> and that is the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 20. 3. Is <hi>Miniſteriall,</hi> and that is, <hi>Pastors, Fathers, Councel-determinations,</hi> and all their right <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structures,</hi> that is, ſo farre as they are conforme to the ſcriptures, <hi>I. Cor. 3. 10. Let every man take heed, how he buildeth thereupon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>ſecond;</hi> I anſwere this <hi>question</hi> negatively, <hi>Whether</hi> 
               <note place="margin">II. Can the church mak or creat grounds. 1 Reaſon.</note> 
               <hi>the Church can make Fundamentals?</hi> that is, if it can produce and procreat that to be a <hi>fundamentall</hi> now, which before was never received as ſuch. Now the <hi>Reaſons</hi> of my deniall are theſe. 1. I ground on the <hi>judgement</hi> of theſe WRITTERS, wherof the firſt is, <hi>Vincentius Lyrin.</hi> who in his book anent profane <hi>Novelties,</hi> chap. 3. hath theſe words, <hi>The Church addes nothing, diminiſhes nothing, changeth nothing, cuts not off neceſſars, propoſes not ſuperfluous things, loſſes not her own, uſurpes not that which belongs to others, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way cares to poliſh what was informed of old, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme what is expreſſed and revealed, and to keep what is defined and confirmed: yea this the Church ſtill intends, that whatever was ſimply beleeved before, ſhould afterwards be more carefully beleeved.</hi> And after him, <hi>G. Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam,</hi> in his Dialogues, <hi>Neither,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>the whole Church, nor a Generall Councell, nor the Pope can make an Article of faith.</hi> Bellar. alſo, lib. 2. de Concil. cap. 12. <hi>The Councells when they</hi> define, <hi>do not make any point defined, to be of infallible trueth, but they onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it to be ſo.</hi> To all which three worthy <hi>ſentences</hi> we ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104070:14"/>
            <p>If the Church could make <hi>fundamentalls,</hi> then it could unmak <note place="margin">2 Reaſon.</note> them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the more moderate of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> deny this, upon this ground, that it belongs to the ſame power, both to creat and annihilate. And ſo they reject that <hi>non obſtante</hi> of the Councel of <hi>Constance,</hi> grounding on that of <hi>Scotus,</hi> 1. diſt. 11. q. 1. <hi>Trueth was of faith before hereſie had a beeing, ſo that the determination of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 Reaſon.</note> 
               <hi>Kirk, doth not make a trueth, though it define againſt an hereſie.</hi> 3. That which the Kirk declares is either <hi>extra</hi> or <hi>intus.</hi> If it be without the nature of the thing declared, then its declaration of the thing is falſe, and ſo it cannot be <hi>fundamentall:</hi> if it be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe and nature of the thing declared, then it is yet onely in that kinde <hi>fundamentall,</hi> ſeing the declaration whatever it be, is poſterior to the nature of the thing. That is but a ſillie <hi>Evaſion</hi> of ſome, to wit, that the declaration of the Church ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a point fundamentall <hi>quoad nos,</hi> nay it doth not that, as the ſame <hi>F. White</hi> well proves, <hi>ibid. p. 9. For no reſpect to us can varie the foundation. if the thing be not fundamentall in the nature of it, the Kirks declaration doth not make it ſo to us.</hi> Since then the Kirk hath no reall <hi>detracting power,</hi> no more, as ſaid is, can it have any reall <note place="margin">4 Reaſon.</note> 
               <hi>adding power,</hi> ſince both are alike forbidden, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 2. 4. All credible points are at laſt reſolved into <hi>Scripture,</hi> therfore, it is it that makes <hi>fundamentalls.</hi> CYPRIAN ſpeaks appoſitly to this purpoſe, <hi>lib.</hi> de Bapt. <hi>All Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, hath its rule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Scripture, here it is bred and borne, and hither it muſt returne.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merarius <hi>lib. 1. Sent. d.</hi> 11. q. 1. <hi>Theologicall principles are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trueths of the ſacred Canons, becauſe the last reſolution of Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall diſcourſe is made unto them, and out of theſe trueths firſtly, each Theologicall Propoſition is deduced.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>QUEST.</hi> What to judge of Creeds and Confeſſions.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Here a needfull <hi>question</hi> comes to be ſolved. as, What are we to judge of the <hi>Creeds, confeſſions, declaratios, formes of faith, ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodal-concluſions,</hi> both of the Antient and Moderne Kirk? for ſince they containe the ſumme of <hi>credenda, agenda, petenda, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa,</hi> that is, of what we are to <hi>beleeve,</hi> to <hi>do,</hi> to <hi>aske,</hi> and to <hi>hope for,</hi> which are the <hi>Synopſis</hi> of all Chriſtian duties, the <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion</hi> is, <hi>If theſe are to be looked upon, as fundamentalls, or grounds of</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Faith and trueth?</hi> To anſwere this aright, let us avoide theſe two <hi>extreams.</hi> 1. None of theſe are ſo to be looked upon as <hi>Scripture,</hi> or of equall authority to it. It was an idol and idle word, that of GREGORY, <hi>to exequat the firſt foure generall Councells to the foure Evangeliſts.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104070:15"/> 2. Avoid that other 1. of the vile <hi>Swenkfeldian,</hi> who in diſputing, <hi>as they reject the Scriptures, ſo alſo all Church determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, pretending (though falſely) that they are oppoſite to Chriſtian liberty.</hi> 3. That of the ARMINIAN, <hi>Who though they admitt the reading of ſuch</hi> Confeſſions <hi>and</hi> declarations, <hi>yet they will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the leaſt authority to them.</hi> The pure Antient Kirk, and our Orthodox preſent kirks oppoſe both theſe, and have publiſhed very needfull and worthy <hi>vſes</hi> of theſe formes. as, 1. They are looked upon as the <hi>Expoſitions</hi> of the true Catholick <hi>Faith.</hi> 2. As <hi>strong barres</hi> both to hold out, and to remove <hi>hereſies.</hi> 3. As a ready <hi>Catechiſme</hi> containing the grounds of both what we are to <hi>beleeve,</hi> &amp; what to <hi>do.</hi> 4. They are a ſingular <hi>Meane,</hi> to beget &amp; preſerve a good <hi>understanding</hi> between kirks, and to foment <hi>Peace, unitie</hi> and <hi>concord</hi> amongſt them, as by the harmonious <hi>Confeſſions</hi> of the Reformed Churches is now ſeen; as when that, which indeed is an Orthodox ground is received, and the Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodox tenet is rejected. That <hi>axiom</hi> of <hi>Lyrin.</hi> was much eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>Quod ſemper, quod ubique, quod ab omnibus creditum eſt.</hi> which ever, and everie-where, and by all is beleeved. In <hi>Ignaetius</hi> his Epiſtles it is often remarked and inculcated, That whoſoever will not joine to the abridged doctrines of the Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hee is corrupted.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">III. Vindication</note>
            </p>
            <p>But paſſing this, I next offer to vindicate this place from the falſe inferences of the <hi>Rhemiſts, Bellarmine, Becan, Tirinus, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. Gretzer.</hi> If the Church bee the <hi>ground of trueth,</hi> then all Chriſtians may &amp; ſhould at laſt acquieſce to its determinations, <note place="margin">1 Ob. anſwered.</note> &amp; ſo ſafely reſolve their <hi>faith</hi> into it at laſt. To which I anſwere firſt, by denying the <hi>Conſequent,</hi> becauſe the Churches Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not the formall cauſe of our aſſent to <hi>divine trueths,</hi> as ſhalbe ſhewen in the Anſwere to the third <hi>Objection.</hi> 2. Giving but not granting what is in the <hi>illation,</hi> yet I deny that to appertain to the preſent Roman Church; which is the maine aime of theſe <hi>Sophiſters.</hi> 3. I propoſe to them this <hi>queſtion,</hi> (which they force us to ſtartle) which is, <hi>What is that Chriſtian Society into which all credible Objects are vltimately reſolved into?</hi> Is it the Antient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Kirk? or is it the lawfull oecumenick Councells? or is it the concurrent judgement of the Antient Fathers? or is it the preſent Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Kirk? To theſe the late <hi>Jeſuits</hi> anſwer far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Moderate <hi>Schoolmen</hi> did. I ſhall ſuccinctly repeat
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104070:15"/> ſome of their moſt abſurd anſwers to this, I meane of the Ieſuits. <hi>Bellarm.</hi> lib. 4. de P. R. chap. 1. <hi>affirmes every ſucceſſour of Peter to be the rock and foundation of trueth.</hi> Gretzer lib. 3. cap. 10. defenſ. <hi>by the Church wee interpret the Pope.</hi> D. Bann. 2. ſecundae. <hi>The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the univerſall Kirk, &amp; that of the Pope, are the ſame.</hi> The Cannon Law, lib. 6. Extravag. tit. 14. <hi>The Reſcripts of the Pope, are Canonicall ſcripture.</hi> D. <hi>John Whyte,</hi> in his way &amp;c. Digreſſ. 16. p. 36. collects out of their Writers, this to be their <hi>judgment.</hi> 1. ſay they, The Catholick Church is the Rule to be followed in all points, as the rule infallible. 2. The Roman and the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Faith</hi> are all one. 3. By the Kirk we mean her Head, ſaieth <hi>Valentia,</hi> tom. 3. d. 1. p. 24. ſo that this Catholick Church, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they ſo much brag, is no other but the <hi>Pope.</hi> Now this <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, finding the bed to be ſhorter then that he can ſtretch himſelf upon it,</hi> as wee have <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28. 20. down right maintains that neither Antient Councells, nor the antient Kirk, nor old Decretalls, nor the preſent Roman Kirk, but the <hi>Pope,</hi> is that, whereunto at laſt we muſt reſolve our <hi>faith.</hi> of which rule to reſolve unto, he ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Analyſ. fidei</hi> lib. 8. cap. 7. <hi>Stante hac regula rationali, animata, infallibili, omnes fidei articuli, ultimatè reſolvuntur in ipſam, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in rationem formalem.</hi> So that according to this new doctrine of the Roman Kirk, <hi>Alexander VII.</hi> now Pope, <hi>is that ground of trueth,</hi> whereon all are to lean; ſo that the <hi>Pope</hi> now, as <hi>D. Clerk</hi> wittily obſerves, is growen ſo bigg, that hee is both <hi>Head</hi> and whole <hi>Body,</hi> yea the whole <hi>Church,</hi> both holy <hi>Father</hi> and holy <hi>Mother,</hi> both <hi>Huſband</hi> and <hi>Wife:</hi> nay <hi>the Pope is God,</hi> as one <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus Sandeus</hi> blaſphemes. This compendious way, that they are fallen upon, puts me in minde of a like fooliſh conceit, one <hi>S. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> a late Ieſuit hath fallen on, who to reject <hi>Bellarmins 15 notes</hi> of the kirk, falls only upon one as ſufficient to confirme <hi>truths,</hi> &amp; confute <hi>errours,</hi> which is the <hi>Miracles of the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church.</hi> Now to ſhew the folly of <hi>Valentia</hi> &amp; ſuch flatterers, heare what to the contrar ſays <hi>J. Picꝰ</hi> in concl. <hi>It may happen that the Pope the vicaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> head be ſick, and as the naturall head ſends down noxious humours into the body, ſo alſo this Vicarian, corrupt doctrines into its body.</hi> But <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teanus</hi> a late Ieſuite is now more plain and bold in his <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m.</hi> on 2. 2. q. 1. a. 6. <hi>That the preſent Pope</hi> (to wit <hi>Paul V.) is Chriſt his true vicar &amp; ſucceſſour, is not not abſolutely belonging to faith: for this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition preſuppoſeth two other Propoſitions. 1. That</hi> Paul the V. <hi>is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104070:16"/> baptiſed 2. That</hi> Paul V. <hi>was Canonically elected to be pope, but ſo it it, that none of theſe two Propoſitions belongs to the Catholick faith.</hi> thus he, out of which I forme this <hi>ſyllogiſme.</hi> Whatſoever <hi>Alexand.</hi> 7. hath defined, that is infallible the <hi>ground of trueth,</hi> but he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that.</hi> Here grant that the <hi>Propoſition</hi> wer true, which yet is moſt falſe; yet its <hi>Aſſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> can be no more then probable. For how can he be certain that this <hi>Pope</hi> was lawfully ordained, or at all baptiſed? Of theſe there is no more then humane <hi>aſſent,</hi> grounded upon probable <hi>conjectures.</hi> or what certainty is there to all and every one ſubject to him, that he hath publiſhed this or that <hi>definition?</hi> Of theſe and the like is no divine certantie. It is excellently well proven by S. V. LYND, That in the Roman Church, which they ſo farre extoll above <hi>Scripture,</hi> there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſafety</hi> nor <hi>certanty,</hi> whether we underſtand the Eſſentiall, or the Repreſentative, or the Virtuall, or the Conſiſtoriall Church, nor that Individuall Church, barbarouſly ſo called, which wants both perſonall and true doctrinall <hi>ſucceſſion.</hi> ſee his <hi>Via devia.</hi> p. 513. and 452. And whereas <hi>Fiſher</hi> and ſome others account it more ſafe to reſolve into the <hi>Councell of Trent</hi> now. I ſay, this can be of no credit at all, becauſe this <hi>Councell</hi> was neither lawfully called, nor was it free, nor was it generally received by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts themſelves, ſee <hi>Innoc. Gentill.</hi> on it, and <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 12. ſee <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitii examen,</hi> ſee <hi>Calvini Antidotum,</hi> ſee the <hi>Hiſtory of the Councell of Trent.</hi> lib. 4. p. 319. ſee <hi>Whyts 3 Conf,</hi> with <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since the <hi>Nicen Creed</hi> hath, <hi>I beleeve in the Church;</hi> Therefore <note place="margin">Ob. 2.</note> primarly &amp; properly, <hi>it is the pillar and ground of trueth.</hi> wherupon <hi>Stapleton</hi> hath this <hi>aſſertion</hi> againſt WHITAKER, <hi>I beleeve, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Church beleeveth</hi> lib. 1. cap. 9. and this indeed is the true ground of their circular argueing, or the COLLIARRS <hi>faith,</hi> and of that brutiſh aſſertion of <hi>Cajetan, That the obedience of a</hi> Brute <hi>is the moſt perfect obedience of any.</hi> But to ſpeake to what is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged of the <hi>Nicen ſymbol.</hi> I anſwere 1. That prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not at all in that <hi>Creed,</hi> it is a falſe quotation of the <hi>Rhemiſts,</hi> like many more. 2. In the Symbol of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> we reade it indeed, and our Divines clearly ſhew, that it was ſpuriouſly foy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in there. 3. Make it to bee the reall compoſure of that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond generall Councell, yet <hi>Druſius,</hi> that great Critick makes it to maintain no more, then <hi>I beleeve the Church.</hi> But 4. <hi>August.</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:104070:16"/> Tom. 10. p. 311. de expoſ. <hi>Symboli,</hi> is of a farre better &amp; ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der judgement, when he ſaid there, <hi>becauſe the Church is not God, therefore wee beleeve not into it, or in it.</hi> Faith <hi>its</hi> credere <hi>as to the Trinitie, ſayes hee, is</hi> conſidere, <hi>but Faiths</hi> credere <hi>as to the reſt or ſecundarie objects of faith, it is but</hi> agnoſcere. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that late Ieſuit-opinion, <hi>I may beleeve in the Kirk, as I beleeve in the Virgin Mary,</hi> neither of theſe is true. Though all the ſuperſtructures of this Church were moſt true, yet all its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions are to be tryed and examined.</p>
            <p>That even in <hi>Auguſtins</hi> judgement, (to whom Proteſtants ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale <note place="margin">Ob. 3.</note> ſo often,) <hi>The Church is the ground of trueth,</hi> when <hi>contra e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistolam fundamenti,</hi> he ſayes, <hi>I would not have beleeved the Gospell, unleſſe the authority of the Church had moved mee.</hi> Now to cleare <hi>August.</hi> and to ſatisfie, as farre as may bee, the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> I anſwer 1. If it be well conſidered againſt whom, and for what <hi>Auguſt.</hi> diſputes there, which both our Divines have ſhewen, and <hi>Papiſts</hi> knew well enough, this teſtimony can make nothing either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, or for them. 2. Some ſchoolmen, as <hi>Scotus, Gabriel, Canus,</hi> judge that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is to be underſtood of acquiſite &amp; hiſtoricall <hi>faith,</hi> and not of infuſed. 3. Others of them thinke, that <hi>Auguſtin</hi> there is ſpeaking of the Authority of that Church, which the Apoſtles governed, &amp; not of the ſucceeding Church. But paſſing them, I anſwer by this <hi>diſtinction,</hi> of the meane, &amp; of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſtinguiſh between</hi> by which, <hi>and</hi> for which.</note> the principall <hi>cauſe.</hi> It is well marked by <hi>Baron.</hi> Apod. Cathol. p. 628. h. 9. q. 4. That wee ought to uſe theſe two Prepoſitions warily, <hi>Per</hi> and <hi>Propter,</hi> that is, <hi>by which,</hi> and <hi>for which</hi> I beleeve. The firſt imports the vſe of <hi>means,</hi> without which <hi>faith</hi> is not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarly produced, but this other relats to the principall ground and formall cauſe of our <hi>aſſent.</hi> And ſo I apply the Churches te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is a meane to beleeve the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> but the principall ground of my <hi>aſſent</hi> to its trueths, is becauſe God hath revealed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſtinguiſh between the</hi> Morall proofe, <hi>&amp; the</hi> Divine proofe.</note> it. I make it yet more cleare by diſtinguiſhing between a <hi>Morall proofe,</hi> and a <hi>Divine proofe,</hi> the Teſtimony of the Church is a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall proofe, motive or inductive of <hi>Faith:</hi> but the Authority of the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking in the ſcriptures is that Divine proofe cauſing <hi>aſſent,</hi> whereunto at laſt I reſolve. <hi>Altiſiedorenſis,</hi> thus explains it. It is with the <hi>beleever</hi> ordinarly, as it was with the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> Ioh. 4. 42. that is, after her diſcovery to them, by the light of grace, they perceive the Divine Majeſty, Wiſdome,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104070:17"/> efficacie, and trueth of Chriſts doctrine, and reſolve into them. and as when a faithfull <hi>Preacher</hi> delivers Apoſtolick doctrine, though by his preaching wee receive theſe trueths, yet we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve not our <hi>faith</hi> principally and finally into his Authority who preaches to us, but into that divine truth that is preached by him. Heare the ſame learned <hi>Baron.</hi> yet clearing this, <hi>As the principall effective cauſe of our</hi> aſſent, <hi>is the Holy Ghost by inward illumination of the minde, and effectuall moving of the will: ſo the word of God it ſelfe revealed, by its innate light, vertue and Majeſty manifeſting its Divinity, is the principall objective cauſe or ground of our</hi> aſſent, <hi>to the trueths of the Gospell.</hi> And after him, <hi>D. Owen,</hi> anent the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Originall of Script. p. 33. <hi>The ſole bottome and foundation, or formall reaſon of our</hi> aſſent <hi>to the Scriptures as Gods Word, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting our hearts and conſciences to theſe Scriptures, is the Authority of God, the ſupream Lord of all, the firſt and only abſolute trueth, ſpeaking in and by the the pen-men of the Scriptures evidenced ſingly in, and by the Scriptures &amp;c.</hi> As for the innate <hi>Arguments</hi> in the ſcriptures, that is, <hi>The Power and Majeſty of the Word, the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the ſtyle, the ingyring light, the conſonancie in it, and in the Writters of it, the divine trueths contained in it, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the like ſhew what a <hi>ground it is to faith,</hi> in ſo much that the Antient Kirk, <hi>Traditor libri,</hi> was judged <hi>Abnegator fidei. But the Papiſts by attributing ſo much to Church-Authority, and detracting ſo much from the Divine-Authority of the Scriptures, and not reſting in them, have fallen into a miſerable and an unextricable Circle.</hi> STAPLETON maintaining in his <hi>Triplicatio,</hi> fol. 188. <hi>That the laſt ground of Faith, is the Authority of the Kirk.</hi> Then the <hi>queſtion</hi> is, By what authority beleeve ye that the Kirk hath <hi>Divine-Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</hi> His <hi>anſwere</hi> is, The <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſay ſo. <hi>Queſtion againe.</hi> By what beleeve ye this? <hi>Anſwers hee,</hi> The Church ſayes ſo. Marke the words of one <hi>H. Holden,</hi> an Engliſhman and <hi>Pariſian</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, lib. 1. cap. 9. <hi>Div. anel. fidei.</hi> (as they are cited by <hi>R. Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> in his ſafe Religion. p. 284.) confeſſing the trueth of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon labyrinth &amp; circular ſhift, in which Divines co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly wont to be involved; <hi>For when they asked, how they know then Scripture to be the revealed Word of God? They anſwere, by the aſſertion of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nverſall cenſenting Church? And if they be againe asked, how they know that this unanimous aſſertion of the Catholick Kirk is free from errour: or infallible? They anſwere, by the Word of GOD;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104070:17"/> thus they unavoydably ſlide into the Circle, moſt filthily dauncing in a ring. The faith, &amp;c.</hi> But as for our <hi>beleefe,</hi> (to cloſe this point) it is thus reſolved. <hi>Wee beleeve the Christian doctrine to be true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the true God is the Authour of it.</hi> We diſcerne that God is the Authour of it both by his intrinſicke, and extrinſicke ſeals or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of it: in that it bearech his <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Superſcription,</hi> &amp; and is confirmed by his undoubted uncontroled <hi>Miracles,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther effects which leade us to the <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O but ſay the <hi>Rhemists</hi> and <hi>Bellarm.</hi> and others; The <hi>Preſence,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ob. 4.</note> the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> the <hi>Prayers</hi> of Chriſt to and for the Church, the <hi>aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of the Holy Spirit to and with the Spouſe and Body of Chriſt, and former experiences towards his inheritance, may make us conclude, that in a proper and ſtrict ſenſe, <hi>the Church is the ground of trueth,</hi> ſo infallible, that it cannot erre in the deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>trueth,</hi> elſe to what end are all theſe its <hi>Priviledges?</hi> Anſ. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
               </label> Let us yeeld all theſe <hi>priviledges</hi> to and of the Church, but what is that to the preſent Roman Church, which is their aime? what a ſlight including argument were this? O Timothy, <hi>know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelfe in Gods houſe, the kirk of</hi> Epheſus, becauſe the Kirk of ROME, <hi>is the ground of trueth,</hi> becauſe to it ar the <hi>promiſes,</hi> becauſe to it is given <hi>infallibilitie?</hi> Is not this a meer begging of the queſtion? The point here is never proven. One particular Church, hath no more particular <hi>priviledges</hi> then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. <hi>Epheſus</hi> is now an Apoſtate, ſo hath <hi>Rome</hi> alſo apoſtatiſed. To cleare my <hi>Anſwere</hi> yet further, I propoſe theſe two <hi>queries.</hi> 1. How can the preſent Roman Kirk be a <hi>ground of trueth,</hi> ſince <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>1</label> it diſagreeth ſo much with it ſelf anent both the nature &amp; num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>fundamentalls?</hi> neither dare its Doctours define either of theſe. My <hi>ſecond querie</hi> is, Where is the <hi>ſeat</hi> of infallibilitie? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>2</label> Who it is, that is the infallible <hi>Judge?</hi> The papiſts of <hi>France</hi> hold that a <hi>Generall Councell</hi> is above the <hi>Pope,</hi> that it is it, that is infallible, ſo do theſe WRITERS, <hi>Cuſanus, Cameracenſis, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Almain, Florent. Panormitan, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Italians</hi> maintaine the flate contrare, and moſt of the <hi>Jeſuits.</hi> O but ſayes BELLARM: <hi>Chriſts prayer for Peter was for faiths infallibilitie both to him and all his ſucceſſours in that Chayre.</hi> but that is flately denied, no more is in <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. but a prayer and promiſe to <hi>Peter</hi> againſt <hi>heart-unbeleefe,</hi> but not a word anent the words of his mouth, nothing anent his pretended <hi>ſucceſſours.</hi> But here yet they object this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104070:18"/> vs, Can that be a true Church, or a ſafe Religion, or way to walk in, which is fallible, but the Proteſtant Church is ſuch, according to our confeſſed tenet? I Anſ. 1. by theſe <hi>diſtinctions.</hi> 1. I diſtinguiſh between a man that may be deceived, and a man that is deceived. 2. between infallibilitie in the <hi>Object,</hi> &amp; in the <hi>Subject.</hi> 3. between infallibilitie in the abſolutely <hi>neceſſar points,</hi> and in ſome inferiour ſmaller <hi>matters,</hi> as is well marked by <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> p. 43. 44. Therefore wee ſay 1. Suppoſe wee ſhould deviat, yet wee have an infallible Rule, the <hi>Word,</hi> though there be much weaknes in the <hi>Recipient,</hi> yet there is ſtill infallibilitie in the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> 2. I affirme, all Churches to be infallible, &amp; that they cannot erre in fundamentalls, <hi>in ſenſis compoſito,</hi> that is, while they remaine true Churches, and deny no eſſentiall of <hi>Faith:</hi> but the ſame <hi>in ſenſis diviſo,</hi> are fallible, that is, when they leave the <hi>Objects</hi> infallibilitie, that is, the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as the Rule of trueth. 3. Wee make a difference between that, <hi>Cui ſubeſſe poteſt falſum,</hi> and that, <hi>Cui actu ſubest falſum.</hi> A man may be deceived, who yet is not deceived. None is <hi>falſus,</hi> or actually deceived, when he beleeves the doctrine of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that is, the holy <hi>Scriptures.</hi> A man may be actually not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, when he is not abſolutely infallible. But laſtly here, they object a paſſage of <hi>August.</hi> who in his Epiſt. 162. ſayes, that <hi>in Romana Eccleſia ſemper viguit Apostolicae Cathedrae principatus.</hi> To which I anſwere, 1. Diſtinguiſh between what <hi>Rome</hi> now is, &amp; when it was ſound. Then was no <hi>Supremacy,</hi> then no viſible <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie,</hi> then no power of both the <hi>ſwords,</hi> then the <hi>Principalitie</hi> was in the profeſſion of a ſound <hi>faith,</hi> in the practiſe of <hi>piety,</hi> in in <hi>prayers,</hi> in <hi>charity,</hi> in <hi>tears</hi> &amp;c. So that this makes nothing for the eſtabliſhment of the tyranny of the preſent Roman Church.</p>
            <p>Now of what I have ſaid, I give theſe generall <hi>Obſerves</hi> and <note place="margin">1 Obſerve.</note> 
               <hi>vſes.</hi> And the firſt ſhall be this. 1. Wherever this divine <hi>trueth</hi> really is, and is ſincerly profeſſed, there is a true Kirk. <hi>Boyd</hi> in his Comment. on <hi>Epheſ.</hi> pag. 335. hath a note appoſite to this. Trueth is the <hi>forme informing</hi> of the Church, and the Church is the <hi>matter informed:</hi> even <hi>as the Candleſtick holds out the Candle, &amp; ſo its light, ſo doth the true Church hold out the light of trueth.</hi> And no leſſe hath <hi>Henſius</hi> a pertinent <hi>note,</hi> on the place to this, <hi>Where God is, there is trueth, &amp; where trueth is, there is the ground of trueth. Our God is a God of trueth,</hi> pſal. 31. 5. and <hi>Chriſt is trueth,</hi> Ioh. 17.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104070:18"/> 14. 6. and <hi>trueth comes by him,</hi> Ioh. 1. 17. and <hi>the gospell is the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell of trueth,</hi> Gal. 3. 1. and <hi>all Worſhippers ſhould worſhip Him in spirit, and in trueth,</hi> Ioh. 4. 23. and where men are <hi>begotten by the Word of trueth,</hi> I am. 1. 18. there I ſay, we may warrantably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, is a true Kirk.</p>
            <p>Then let this be the firſt <hi>uſe</hi> wee make of this point; IT is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent to all the true <hi>Members</hi> of this true Kirk, to be for <note place="margin">2 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> the <hi>Trueths</hi> holden out and profeſſed in it, <hi>II. Cor.</hi> 13. 8. For this end, follow theſe precepts and practiſes of holy men here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. As 1. <hi>Chooſe the trueth,</hi> with DAVID, pſal. 119. 30. 2. <hi>Love the trueth</hi> with ZECHARY, chap. 8. 19. 3. <hi>Buy the trueth</hi> with SOLOMON, prov. 23. 23. 4. <hi>Pray for its propagation</hi> with CHRIST himſelf, Ioh. 17. and 17. pſal. 43. 3. 5. <hi>Speak the truth</hi> with PAUL, Eph. 4. 25. 6. <hi>Walk in the trueth</hi> as GAIUS, Ioh. 3. 3. and pſal. 86. 11. 7. <hi>Pray with</hi> David <hi>to be lead in the trueth,</hi> pſal. 25. 5. 8. <hi>Execute the judgement of trueth,</hi> ZECHAR. 8. 16. 9. <hi>Beare witneſſe unto the trueth</hi> as <hi>John Baptist</hi> did, Ioh. 5. 33. 10. <hi>Have your loines girt about with the girdle of trueth,</hi> Eph. 6. 14. 11. <hi>And be yee eſtabliſhed in the preſent trueth,</hi> II. Pet. 1. 12. 12. <hi>Teach the way of God in trueth,</hi> Matth. 22. 16. II. Cor. 4. 2. Therefore my third <hi>vſe</hi> is,</p>
            <p>Let Miniſters learne, <hi>to divide the word of trueth aright;</hi> in this do as <hi>Paul</hi> bids, <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 2. 15. and in this do as <hi>Paul</hi> did, ſee <note place="margin">3 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> 
               <hi>II. Cor.</hi> 4. 2. and <hi>II. Cor.</hi> 6. 4. 7. ſee alſo pſal. 40. 11. <hi>I have not hid thy trueth from the great Congregation.</hi> As there are two ſorts of <hi>Builders,</hi> which made <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, <hi>Let each take heed how hee builds, I. Cor.</hi> 3. 10. ſo there are of <hi>Dividers</hi> of the word of truth. Which made our Lord to ſay, what we reade <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 42. 43. as for <hi>Builders,</hi> ſome, their building is the ſuperſtructure of ſound <hi>trueths,</hi> conſiſting well with, and decoring the foundation: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are of <hi>errours,</hi> deforming, defacing, and deſtroying the foundation, <hi>as ſtraw upon marble, whoſe worke ſhall be burnt.</hi> As for <hi>Dividers,</hi> ſome overſlipping, mangling, and renting, and by wreſting of it, <hi>do it to their own perdition.</hi> So others againe, they purely, plainly, powerfully, impartially apply the word to the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of every man in the ſight of Ieſus. Well is it amplified and enlarged by <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> how diverſe wayes a faithfull <hi>Paſtor</hi> is bound to divide the word of trueth, and that to perſons diverſly affected. I ſhall but touch onely ſome few of his <hi>dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104070:19"/> 1. Looke how a <hi>Paſtor</hi> is to carry towards a <hi>Beleever,</hi> and how towards an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeleever.</hi> 2. How towards the <hi>Young,</hi> and how towards the <hi>old,</hi> within the Kirk. 3. How towards, <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours,</hi> how towards <hi>equall</hi> and <hi>inferiours.</hi> 4. How towards <hi>Humble spirits,</hi> and how towards the <hi>Proud.</hi> 5. How towards <hi>Weak,</hi> and how towards <hi>Malitious ſinners.</hi> 6. How towards the <hi>Penitents,</hi> and how towards <hi>impenitents.</hi> 7. How toward. <hi>Turbulent spirits,</hi> and how towards <hi>peaceable.</hi> 8. How towards <hi>Proficients</hi> in Chriſts ſchool, &amp; how towards <hi>deficients</hi> 9. How to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards orderly <hi>Walkers,</hi> and how towards the <hi>ſcandalous.</hi> 10. How towards <hi>Faithfull Pastors,</hi> &amp; how towards idle <hi>Belly-gods.</hi> See theſe and many more in that Treatiſe of his <hi>de cura pasto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali.</hi> O if this ſhould move and work us up, into a <hi>Fabian-like</hi> cunctation and long pauſing! O that wee could view ſeriouſly, and conſider carefully, <hi>the length, the breadth, the hight, and depth of that myſterie of godlineſſe, which is the right dividing of the word of trueth!</hi> O how loath ſhould wee be without an inward <hi>Call</hi> to undertake this charge <hi>of laying foundations,</hi> ſuch a burden, ſayes <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> that the very Angels themſelves would tremble to undergo it. This made <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 3. <hi>Thriſe refuſe it,</hi> &amp; ſo Ezek. chap. 14. and ſo <hi>Jonas,</hi> chap. 1. This made AMBROSE, <hi>hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and three times flee from</hi> Millan. This made <hi>Gregory Nazianz.</hi> to flee twiſe to the ſtudy of <hi>Philoſophy.</hi> This made <hi>Augustine</hi> to weepe, and to deprecat the <hi>Epiſcopall function,</hi> (put upon him by <hi>Valerian</hi> in theſe tearmes; <hi>quidvis? ut peream?</hi> as if it ſtood him as much upon, as his <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>ſoules</hi> ſalvation came unto: <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Valerian.</hi> Which made <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> againe to ſay, <hi>Hom.</hi> 3. in act. Apoſt. <hi>I beleeve not, that many Miniſters of the Church are ſaved, when I conſider the greatneſſe of their Charge, and their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence therin.</hi> This made <hi>Paul</hi> I. Tim. 3. 6. to ſay, <hi>Not a novice, leſt being lifted up with pride, he fall into the conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation of the devill.</hi> Let us then look well to this, how we have entered into it? <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſayes, this will be one of the Lords <hi>queries</hi> at the laſt day, <hi>quomodo intrasti?</hi> Sad and ſtrict will be, one day, the account that young <hi>Novices</hi> muſt give, for ruſhing upon the burden of the paſtorall <hi>Charge.</hi> GREGORY in that ſame book, p. 3. cap. 26. affirmes, <hi>That it is as dangerous for ſuch Novices to undergo the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of a paſtorall Charge, as to lay the roofe of the houſe upon the wals when they are green.</hi> this were to <hi>ruine</hi> and not to <hi>build.</hi> And for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104070:19"/> any burden, that ſuch or the moſt part ſuſtaine in the Church, ſuch <hi>Novices</hi> are well compared, (by the Authour of the <hi>Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> p. 12. <hi>to theſe little</hi> ſtatues <hi>or</hi> Angelets, <hi>that wee often ſee affixed to the</hi> pillars <hi>of our Churches ſtooping the head &amp; bending the back, as if they did ſupport the whole</hi> fabricke, <hi>and yet they ſuſtaine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, but are rather themſelves ſupported. Have wee not ſeen the trees of the Forreſt, offer to rest themſelves under the ſhadow of this brier, and what was the iſſue a fire came out of the brier, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the Cedars of Lebanon?</hi> What a prepoſterous <hi>Courſe</hi> is it, to ruſh on vpon the publiſhing of <hi>divine trueths,</hi> who were never acquainted much with either <hi>naturall</hi> or <hi>morall trueths?</hi> O that <hi>Youngman</hi> aiming at this would but ſtay, till they ſhould finde themſelves <hi>indued with power from above,</hi> and furniſhed with <hi>gifts</hi> meete for ſo high a <hi>Calling! Hee that is the teacher of Angels,</hi> (ſayes the ſame GREGORY there) <hi>would not be the teacher of men, before 30 years of age.</hi> O how many things at neceſſary to the well manageing of right <hi>ſuperſtructures,</hi> ſuch as lively preaching theſe <hi>trueths,</hi> right adminiſtration of <hi>Sacraments</hi> confirming theſe <hi>trueths,</hi> frequent Catechiſing to beare in theſe <hi>trueths</hi> upon peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>viſitation</hi> of the ſicke, to refreſh them with the Memorialls of divine <hi>trueths.</hi> Spirituall <hi>conference</hi> upon all occaſions in all <hi>meetings,</hi> that we may mutually be edified in our holy faith. The <hi>power</hi> and <hi>vſe</hi> of the <hi>keyes,</hi> whereby <hi>strong holds are ſubdued, which oppoſe the trueth and power of godlineſſe!</hi> Then what a man of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> ſhould ſuch an one be, that undertaks by theſe means, the ſuperſtructures of a holy <hi>life</hi> upon this ground? Since we ar <note place="margin">4 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> to be built on this <hi>ground,</hi> it is needfull, (both by the neceſſity of the <hi>meane,</hi> and of the <hi>precept)</hi> that we by all laudable endeavours ſtudy to know them, that we may the more readily beleeve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and practiſe what is practicable of them, and this both for our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with Chriſt and our more ſtrict <hi>Communion</hi> with his body. IT could not be but a great <hi>error</hi> of theſe Biſhops, who did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine <hi>Syneſius</hi> to be the Biſhop of <hi>Ptolemais,</hi> when as he did not beleeve that maine foundation, of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> as is reported by <hi>Photius</hi> and by <hi>Evagrius.</hi> For though I willingly yeeld and grant, that alike explicite and diſtinct knowledge of all revealed <hi>trueths</hi> is not of the ſame degree of neceſſity required, (for as wee diſtinguiſh betweene <hi>Fundamentalls,</hi> and <hi>ſuprafundamentalls,</hi> and <hi>Circumfundamentalls,</hi> all which three are revealed <hi>trueths,</hi> ſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104070:20"/> alſo between theſe <hi>aſſents</hi> given to theſe, as for <hi>example,</hi> though a man cannot be ſaved without an expreſſe <hi>aſſent</hi> to prime <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentalls</hi> when they are clearly propoſed &amp; ſufficiently revealed to him. Yet as for others, not of ſo needfull concerment, that are not ſo clearly holden out, a man without the expreſſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct knowledge of theſe may be ſaved) Yet this is not affirmed to maintaine or to juſtifie, but rather to condemne that affected, that groſſe, and vincible <hi>ignorance</hi> of the moſt needfull and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall grounds of the Chriſtian <hi>faith,</hi> yea of very neceſſarie <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructures</hi> O how many are ignorant of the firſt foundations of Chriſtianity? May not the Lord charge <hi>Paſtors</hi> with this, <hi>my People periſh for lack of knowledge?</hi> How can one ſay, <hi>he is built on the Rock,</hi> that knows it not? How can any reſolve a <hi>Caſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> dexterouſly, when he knows not the <hi>grounds</hi> on which it depends, and muſt be reſolved by? I ſhall onely reflect now vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſad and groſſe <hi>ignorance</hi> of the foure maine neceſſary points. As 1. O what ignorance is of Chriſt a Saviour, what <hi>worth</hi> is in him, what <hi>neceſſity</hi> of it, and therfore how little is he imployed in his <hi>Natures</hi> and <hi>Offices?</hi> what <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>benefite</hi> by it? 2. O what defect is now among co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Profeſſours, anent the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>fin,</hi> the <hi>nature</hi> of it, the wofull <hi>conſequents</hi> of it? how few do charge themſelves with it? and that makes men make a mocke of it, and are fearleſſe of any danger by it. 3. O what ignorance is now of true repentance <hi>from dead works?</hi> Who <hi>mourns</hi> now for the ſinnes of the <hi>Tymes,</hi> or of the <hi>Places</hi> hee lives in, or of his <hi>Calling,</hi> or of his <hi>Relations?</hi> Where is the <hi>Paſtor</hi> that ſayes, <hi>quid feci?</hi> Where is there a reall <hi>Amendement,</hi> a through <hi>Reformation,</hi> or where are <hi>ſincere Converts.</hi> 4. O what igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is there of the nature of <hi>faith</hi> towards God? of <hi>faith</hi> in a ſlain Saviour, of <hi>faith unfained and working by love?</hi> If there wer no more <hi>defects</hi> of needfull <hi>Credibles</hi> amongſt us, theſe ar ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to draw down great, yea all wrath on us. But on theſe I inſiſt no more now; Onely one word, and that is, I wiſh Miniſters and all Chriſtians to be more carefull about <hi>fundamentalls,</hi> then about <hi>extra-fundamentalls, ſubſtances</hi> then <hi>circumſtances, bodies</hi> then <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, eſſentialls</hi> then <hi>ritualls</hi> and <hi>ceremonies,</hi> to be more for <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanties,</hi> then for <hi>uncertancies,</hi> more for <hi>neceſſaries,</hi> then <hi>unneſſaries,</hi> more for the <hi>weyghtie things of the Law,</hi> then for the <hi>tything of avice, mint,</hi> and <hi>Cumin,</hi> more for Catholick <hi>verities,</hi> then for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104070:20"/> 
               <hi>opinions,</hi> and to lay the ſtreſſe of the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the <hi>former</hi> and not upon the <hi>latter.</hi> That <hi>Rabies quorundam Theologorum,</hi> (ſo it is well called) conteſting about <hi>trifles,</hi> and quarreiling about a needleſſe <hi>Rite,</hi> under the pretence of obvia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>errours,</hi> and maintaining <hi>trueths</hi> hath ruined vs. The like of this did bring in the ARIAN <hi>hereſie,</hi> as <hi>Hilare</hi> reports, and this day to our great griefe wee may ſee, how much our needleſſe <hi>Contests</hi> do ſtrengthen our common <hi>Enemy,</hi> I meane the <hi>Papiſt.</hi> Miniſters that are more of Catholick then factious ſpirits will think on this, and mourne for it, and help to amend it.</p>
            <p>Now I addreſſe my ſelf to ſpeake a word of that laſt thing that I propoſed, and that is, anent our <hi>Relation</hi> to that <hi>Pillar and ground of trueth.</hi> That is, <hi>How to behave our ſelves as to it.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> argues a <hi>Behaviour</hi> or <hi>Converſation</hi> ſutable and proportioned to the <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Call:</hi> without which no <hi>Houſe,</hi> no <hi>Republique,</hi> no <hi>Army,</hi> no <hi>Church</hi> can ſubſiſt. When men know and follow what their <hi>place</hi> and their <hi>station</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, then their <hi>behaviour</hi> is, as it ought. I ſhall firſt ſhew the meaning of the <hi>Word,</hi> and the nature of the <hi>Converſation</hi> here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and then make ſome <hi>applications.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the firſt. There is a twofold <hi>Converſation</hi> or <hi>Behaviour</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Two-fold Converſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1 Evill.</note> ſpoken of. The firſt is, from our <hi>Birth,</hi> to our <hi>Effectuall Calling.</hi> This is called by PETER, <hi>vaine, I. Pet.</hi> 1. 18. and <hi>filthy, II. Pet.</hi> 2. 7. and by PAUL, <hi>the former,</hi> Eph. 4. 22. and by ISAIAH, <hi>baſe,</hi> cap. 3. 5. 2. Is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt period of our <hi>Effectuall Calling,</hi> to the end of our chriſtian <hi>Race.</hi> This <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Converſation</hi> or <hi>Behaviour,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Good,</note> hath in <hi>Scripture</hi> many <hi>Names.</hi> IT is called a <hi>Good Converſation,</hi> Iam. 3. 13. I. Pet. 3. 16. &amp; I. Tim. 3. 2. a <hi>Good Behaviour,</hi> &amp; if this had been in ſome <hi>Miniſters,</hi> then there had not been ſo unſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo ranting, ſo ſchiſmaticall <hi>Miſcarriage</hi> amongſt vs. IT is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">Holy.</note> alſo an <hi>Holy Converſation,</hi> I. Pet. 3. 15. IT is called an <hi>Honeſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Honeſt.</note> 
               <hi>Converſation,</hi> I. Pet. 2. 12. If this were well looked unto, then ſuch vanitie in <hi>Apparrell,</hi> in <hi>geſtures, &amp;c.</hi> would not be amongſt us, wee that are Miniſters had need now, to be under that tye of <note place="margin">Chaſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright Orderly Heavenly Examplar Gospel Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</note> the 16 Canon. of the vij Gen. Councell at CONSTANT, <hi>de habitu Clericorum.</hi> IT is called a <hi>Chaſt Converſation,</hi> ſo I. Pet. 3. 2. IT is called an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright Converſation,</hi> pſal. 37. 14. IT is called <hi>Orderlie,</hi> pſal. 50. 23. IT is called an <hi>Heavenly Converſation,</hi> Phil. 3. 20. IT is called <hi>Examplar,</hi> I. Tim. 4. 12. IT is called a <hi>Gospel-Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:104070:21"/> Phil. 1. 27. IT is called a <hi>Converſation in ſimplicity,</hi> and in <note place="margin">Godlie.</note> 
               <hi>godly ſincerity,</hi> II. Cor. 1. 12. And as the <hi>Behaviour</hi> thus qualified, and inveſted with theſe <hi>Properties,</hi> is requiſite to ſaintſhip of all <hi>profeſſours,</hi> ſo is it much more in Miniſters, both as to their perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, as alſo to their vocationall <hi>Converſation.</hi> This moved PAUL, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 7. to exhort thus, <hi>Remember them that have the rule over you, who have ſpoken unto you, the word of God, whoſe faith follow, conſidering the end of their Converſation.</hi> And as to that end, mark his own <hi>practiſe</hi> worthily and largely ſet down, <hi>I. Theſſ. 2. verſ.</hi> 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>But to returne to the words as ſpoken to <hi>Timothy.</hi> I propoſe this DOCTRINE; <hi>A Miniſters behaviour or converſation, (which is his conſtant courſe of walking) ſhould not onely be raiſed above the light of nature, but it ſhould be ſutable and anſwerable to theſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious trueths revealed in the Scriptures, as alſo to all the Ordinances of the Goſpell, which he adminiſters and holds out.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Manner of of our beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. I. Prudently.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To illuſtrate this, I ſhall now hold out ſomething as to the way and manner of a Miniſters <hi>behaviour,</hi> that as a Miniſter, <hi>he may adorne the doctrine of God our Saviour, in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let the Miniſter learne to carry prudently in diſpenſing Gods <hi>Myſteries,</hi> he muſt go on with them by degrees. <hi>Milk muſt go before ſtrong meat. Give as wiſe ſtewarts, to each their portion in due ſeaſon,</hi> Luk. 12. 42. firſt teach the <hi>ſimple Principles,</hi> before wee fall upon <hi>Perfections.</hi> Go not beyond the <hi>hearers</hi> capacities. <hi>Greg. Nyſſen.</hi> ſayes well, <hi>As wee teach not Infants the deepe precepts of</hi> ſcience, <hi>but firſt</hi> letters, <hi>and then</hi> ſyllabs, <hi>&amp;c. ſo the</hi> Guides <hi>of the Church, do firſt propound to their hearers</hi> certain documents, <hi>which are as the</hi> Elements, <hi>and ſo by degrees do open to them, the more perfect and myſterious</hi> matters. <hi>Exceſſe beyond Capacities makes deficients &amp; not Proficients,</hi> ſayes <hi>Auguſt.</hi> lib, 12. <hi>de Civit. Dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, preach the word,</hi> II. Tim. 4. 2. <note place="margin">II Diligentlie.</note> 
               <hi>Exhort with all long-ſuffering,</hi> ſayes PAUL, inſtructing <hi>Timothyes</hi> behaviour. A ſad wo ſhall be upon the careleſſe <hi>mynde,</hi> and the lazie <hi>hand,</hi> &amp; upon the dumb <hi>mouth.</hi> O let us with all our might indeavour to ſet up the throne of Ieſus Chriſt, in hearts, and in Congregations. <hi>A neceſſity is laid upon mee, and woe unto mee, if I preach not the Gospell.</hi> Great is the <hi>task</hi> we have in hand, heavie is that burden laid on our ſhoulders, daylie <hi>ſow, harrow, break up, water</hi> and <hi>plant,</hi> and waite for the Lords <hi>increaſe.</hi> IT was a good
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104070:21"/> word of GREG. in his Morals. <hi>If I do not beſtirre me,</hi> Sathan <hi>may prevaile, the people everlaſtingly periſh, &amp; their blood bee required at my hand.</hi> O labour then, yea <hi>though it ſhould be in vain</hi> Iſai. 49. 4. 5. <hi>Yet the Lord ſent his ſervants the Prophets riſing early, &amp;c.</hi> and in nothing ſhall our <hi>labour</hi> be approven more, then in inſtructing the <hi>ignorant</hi> by Catechiſing. This was the firſt <hi>meane,</hi> wherby we gained <hi>ground</hi> on POPERY, and the bleſſed <hi>event</hi> of it made <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to ſay, <hi>Ego profecto profitear me eſſe diſcipulum Catechiſmi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is laying aſide <hi>all ſelfe, all by-ends, all private interests,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">III. Sincerlie.</note> for a wrong <hi>end</hi> will marre the <hi>work.</hi> It is not a pure <hi>behaviour</hi> to undergo this <hi>Charge,</hi> meerly for worldly <hi>Lucre</hi> or <hi>Livelyhood,</hi> 1. Pet. 5. 2. Gods <hi>glory</hi> and mans <hi>ſalvation</hi> aimed at, is a manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our <hi>Miniſtery</hi> as becomes. IT is well ſaid of <hi>Baxter,</hi> p. 117. of his Reform. Paſtor. <hi>Self deniall is of a double neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a Pastor, as he hath a double Sanctification or Dedication to GOD. All our studies and knowledge and excellent preaching will not availe, if the ends be not right.</hi> Marke <hi>Pauls</hi> vindications as to this, I <hi>cor. 2. 1. Hee came not with excellency of speech, or of wiſdom, or with intyſing words of mans wiſdome,</hi> v. 6. and II. <hi>Cor. 2. 17. For we are not as many which corrupt the word of God: but as of ſincerity, but as of God, in the ſight of God, speak wee in CHRIST.</hi> And chap. 4. 2. <hi>but have renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſtie, not walking in craftineſſe, nor handling the word of GOD deceitfully, but by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the trueth, commending our ſelves to every mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the ſight of GOD.</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>For wee preach not our ſelves, but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord.</hi> O that ſome, whoſe preaching is all for crying up themſelves, and for crying down others, would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this <hi>Patern!</hi> And chap. 5. verſ. 12. <hi>For wee commend not our ſelves againe to you.</hi> Chap. 6. 4. <hi>But in all things approving our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves as the Miniſters of God, &amp;c.</hi> II. Cor. 7. 12. <hi>I wrote unto you, that our care for you in the ſight of God might appeare unto you.</hi> II. Cor. 8. 21. <hi>Providing honeſt things not only in the ſight of the Lord, but in the ſight of men.</hi> Chap. 10. 3. <hi>Though we walk in the fleſh, yet we do not warre after the fleſh. 14. For we ſtretch not our ſelves beyond our meaſure. 18 For not he that commendeth himſelf is approven, but whom the Lord commendeth.</hi> And chap. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 14. <hi>For I ſeek not yours but you. 17. Did I make a gaine of you? 19. But wee do all things dearly beloved, for your edifying.</hi> See alſo what he ſayes of theſe, <hi>that preach not Chriſt ſincerly,</hi> phil. 1. 15, 16, ſee I. Tim. 6. 5. <hi>Who
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104070:22"/> ſuppoſe that gaine is godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let a <hi>Paſtor</hi> that minds good <hi>Behaviour</hi> in Gods <hi>Houſe,</hi> inſiſt <note place="margin">IV. Diſcretlie and fitlie.</note> upon what is needfull and fitting his people, in the whole courſe of his Miniſtery, both for matter and manner, and for what is fitteſt for the times be lives in, <hi>Neceſſity</hi> ſhould teach him <hi>beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> in all theſe. Let <hi>diſcretion</hi> teach them to bee obſervant of the caſe of their flocks. Above all, labour to teach <hi>Chriſt crucified</hi> to our people, and if this be well taught, we teach them all; <hi>that</hi> being <hi>the one thing neceſſarie. Diſcretion</hi> will teach a <hi>Paſtor</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide <hi>needleſſe Ornaments,</hi> which argue little inward worth, and <hi>unprofitable Controverſies,</hi> and <hi>trifling debates.</hi> See II. Tim. 2. 16. <hi>But ſhun profan and vaine bablings, &amp;c.</hi> I. Tim. 6. 5. <hi>Perverſe diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of men of corrupt mindes.</hi> II. Tim. 2. 23. <hi>but fooliſh and unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned queſtions avoide</hi> I. Tim. 6. 20. <hi>Avoide oppoſitions of ſcience, falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſo called Diſcretion</hi> will teach him not to trouble his Auditory with old <hi>hereſies</hi> which time hath confuted, nor with to curious <hi>Caſes</hi> of Conſciences of that nature, that it is harder to finde the <hi>Caſe,</hi> then the <hi>Reſolution.</hi> Diſcret <hi>behaviour</hi> will teach a <hi>Paſtor</hi> to envy moſt againſt the ſinnes of the preſent times. IT is well marked of our Lord, that he never envyed ſo much againſt <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> and <hi>Sabbath-breaking,</hi> becauſe theſe were not the ſinnes of the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>places</hi> he preached in, as againſt <hi>spirituall Pride, hypocriſie,</hi> and <hi>traditions,</hi> which were then moſt predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant amongſt theſe people, then it ſhall alſo be looked upon as a <hi>diſcret behaviour</hi> to whipe <hi>vices,</hi> but to ſpare <hi>Perſons,</hi> for by ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and perſonall <hi>Reflexions,</hi> and by baſe railing <hi>asperſions,</hi> this is the reſult, that thereby the hearts of the <hi>Righteous</hi> are ſadded, and the hands of the <hi>wicked</hi> are ſtrengthened, as is to much pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable here-away. A diſcret <hi>behaviour</hi> will diſtinguiſh betweene blind <hi>Furie</hi> and cold <hi>Luke-warmneſſe.</hi> A diſcret <hi>behaviour</hi> will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate the <hi>Preacher</hi> ſo, that he will endeavour more for choiſe <hi>matter,</hi> then for <hi>Ornaments</hi> made up of words. Uſually the plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>dreſſe</hi> is moſt ſubſtantiall. Follow <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Counſell <hi>lib.</hi> de Catechiſ. rud. <hi>Preferre the ſentence to words, as the ſoule is preferred to the body. Mallem,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>veriores quam diſertiores invenire ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones, ſicut mallem prudentiores qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> formoſiores habere amices.</hi> keep between baſe ſcurrilitie, and affected frothie gaudie ſpeech. O that wee would learne to ſpeake the pure language of <hi>Canaan!</hi> O that every <hi>Paſtor</hi> might ſay with ISAIAH, chap. 5. 4. <hi>The Lord
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104070:22"/> hath given me the tongue of the learned, that I would know how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to him that is weary!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no better <hi>Pulpit-behaviour</hi> then that which is mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <note place="margin">V. Humblie.</note> by <hi>humilitie, meekneſſe</hi> and <hi>Condeſcenſion, A Teacher,</hi> as is well ſaid of AUGUST <hi>ſhould be ready both to teach and learne at once.</hi> Wee ſhould not be as ſome proudly venting our own <hi>Conceits</hi> and <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities,</hi> and diſdaining all, and flinging at all, that any way contradict us. As if the <hi>Chayre</hi> were onely ours, wee the <hi>Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liels,</hi> and all others the <hi>Pauls</hi> at our feet. Can <hi>pryde</hi> leade men to heaven? if <hi>pryde</hi> did thurſt out of heaven proud Angels, will heaven let in proud <hi>Preachers?</hi> Remember <hi>That being a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, thou art the ſervant of all for Chriſts ſake. Learne of me</hi> matth. 11. 28. ſee phil. 2. <hi>Hee humbled himſelf &amp;c.</hi> Our unfitneſſe, the ſublimitie of the <hi>Charge,</hi> the weight of the <hi>matter,</hi> &amp; the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Him</hi> whoſe Meſſage wee carry, may teach us to be humble. The pryde of <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> of <hi>Arius, Pelagius, Aërius,</hi> was their ruine, being for it deſerted of God, &amp; abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all good men. Avoide then both <hi>Arrogancie</hi> and <hi>ſillineſſe.</hi> If men beleeved the <hi>preſence</hi> of God there, and what he <hi>promiſes</hi> there, and how ſadlie he will rebuke all <hi>affronts</hi> done to him there: O how humble, O how reverent would we be in our <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachs</hi> thither! <hi>Reverence, fervencie</hi> and <hi>humility,</hi> how much are theſe requiſite in all our divine <hi>adminiſtrations?</hi> Heare the ſame <hi>Baxter,</hi> ibid. p. 128. <hi>I hate that preaching which tendeth to make the hearers laugh, or to move their mindes with tackling levity, and affect them as Stage-playes vſe to do, in ſtead of affecting them with a holy reverence of the Name of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Behaviour</hi> in Gods houſe, is onely beſt of theſe who are <note place="margin">VI. Spirituallie</note> indeed poſſeſſed by the Holy Ghoſt, happy are theſe that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by him, and that in all their wayes ſavour of the things of the Spirit. A ſpirituall <hi>ſtraine</hi> in preaching, and in all other acts of ſpiritualitie, is ſuch that ſpirituall <hi>hearers</hi> can diſcerne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. There be ſome that even when they ſpeak of ſpirituall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, talk even of them not in a ſpirituall, but meete carnall way, as if they were but common and triviall. Alace for this obſerve, That commonly theſe that are learned men, are not the moſt ſpirituall men, <hi>I. Cor. 1. 26. 27. Gregor.</hi> in his Moralls, lib. 33. <hi>Deus primo colligit indoctos: poſtmodum Philoſophos; et non per Oratores docuit Piſcatores, ſed per Piſcatores ſubegit Oratores.</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:104070:23"/> Remember theſe worthie ſpeeches of PAUL. Rom. 1. 11. <hi>I long to ſee you, that I may impart unto you ſome spirituall gift.</hi> I. Cor. 2. 14. <hi>Spirituall things are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> verſ. 15. <hi>The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall man judgeth all things.</hi> Gal. 6. 5. <hi>Yee which are spirituall, restore ſuch a man, with the ſpirit of meeknes</hi> I. Cor. 9. 11. (there it is ſuppoſed) <hi>that wee ſhould ſow ſpirituall things.</hi> I Cor. 10. 3. U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that, it is affirmed, <hi>That all did eat the ſame ſpirituall meat. &amp; that all did drink the ſame ſpirituall drink.</hi> I. Cor. 14. 12. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are there, Zealous of spirituall gifts.</hi> And why are <hi>Paſtors</hi> or <hi>Prophets</hi> thought to be <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> (as I. Cor. 14. 37?) is it not <hi>that men ſhould bee ſpiritually minded?</hi> Rom. 8. 6 is it not, <hi>That men may bee built up a spirituall houſe, an holy Prieſthood to offer up spirituall ſacrifice</hi> as <hi>I. Pet.</hi> 2. 5.?</p>
            <p>Hee hath a good <hi>Pulpit behaviour,</hi> that ſpeaks ſo to the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city <note place="margin">VII. Plainly and familiarly.</note> of <hi>hearers,</hi> that it is well underſtood by them. IT is often found the greateſt buſſineſſe of an honeſt Miniſter, to make a needfull high point of <hi>Divinity</hi> plaine and evident to <hi>Alphabeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi> Painted obſcure <hi>Sermons</hi> are like the painted <hi>glaſſe</hi> in the windowes that keep out the <hi>Light,</hi> and they ar to oft the marks of painted <hi>Hypocrites.</hi> Of old the <hi>Valentiniani</hi> and <hi>Bafilidiani,</hi> and of late the <hi>Swenkfeldians, Weigelians, Enthuſiaſts</hi> and the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſians,</hi> purpoſly obſcured their fantaſticall and fanaticall <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> in obſcure and obſolet words. Thus they masked their <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors;</hi> but <hi>Trueth</hi> ever loves the light of <hi>Evidence.</hi> And indeed there is no better way to make a good <hi>Cauſe</hi> prevaile, then to make it as plain and throughly known, as wee can. Wee ſhould not be <hi>Barbarians</hi> one to another. Marke that of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 28. 11. cited by <hi>Paul,</hi> I. Cor. 14. 21. <hi>With men of other tongues will I speak to them, &amp;c.</hi> Affected <hi>obſcuritie</hi> in revealing divine <hi>Trueths,</hi> looks both <hi>ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lyke,</hi> as alſo <hi>Judgement-like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miniſters ſhould remember what <hi>Paul</hi> hath, <hi>I. Cor. 4. 20. The</hi> 
               <note place="margin">VIII. Powerfully.</note> 
               <hi>Kingdome of God is not in word, but in power.</hi> And <hi>II. Cor. 10. 4. 5. The weapons of our warefare, &amp;c.</hi> Our words ſhould be ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to pierce ſtonie <hi>hearts</hi> as nailes. <hi>Coldneſſe</hi> in preaching and ſleepie <hi>dulneſſe</hi> is not for gaining of unmortified <hi>spirits.</hi> Yet I wiſh a prudent mixture of <hi>ſeveritie</hi> and <hi>mildneſſe</hi> both in our preaching and in our diſcipline, for if there bee no powerfull <hi>ſeverity,</hi> then there will be a contempt of our <hi>Reproofs:</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine if all were powerfull <hi>ſeveritie,</hi> wee ſhould then be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104070:23"/> rather <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> of Dominion, then <hi>Perſwaders</hi> of the minds of men to the <hi>trueth.</hi> That is a golden Rule that <hi>Gregor</hi> ibid. hath. <hi>Miſcenda eſt lenitas cum ſeveritate, et faciendum ex vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quoddam temperamentum, vt nec multa asperitate exulcerentur ſubdits nec ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nia benignitate ſolvantur.</hi> Away then on the one hand, with baſe <hi>Cowardlineſſe,</hi> and on the other, with dogged <hi>ſeveritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All our <hi>Behaviour</hi> relating to the <hi>Flock,</hi> ſhould be carried on <note place="margin">IX. Lovinglie.</note> in tender <hi>love</hi> to them. It was a good word of <hi>Paul,</hi> I. Cor. 16. 24. <hi>My love be with you all.</hi> Marke another, II. Cor. 11. 11. <hi>Why? becauſe I love you not? God knoweth.</hi> And a third, II. Cor. 12. 15. <hi>Though the more I love you, the leſſe I be loved of you.</hi> Wee ſhould make them ſee, that our <hi>love</hi> is to their <hi>ſoules,</hi> to their <hi>spirituall good:</hi> that nothing pleaſes us more, then what profits them, and that nothing troubleth us more, then their hurt. We muſt be as Fathers to them, <hi>till Christ be formed in them.</hi> Wee may be ſure of this, that when the people ſhall ſee us unfainedly love them, they will heare us, and beare with us, and follow us the more willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and ſpeedily. How can it be otherwiſe when they ſee, <hi>That we spend and are spent for their ſakes?</hi> yet this is not ſaid, to remove all <hi>ſharpneſſe</hi> to them, as inconſiſtant with <hi>love.</hi> O no! Parents will correct their <hi>Children,</hi> ſo doth <hi>GOD,</hi> ſo ſhould the <hi>Miniſter.</hi> O but let there be mutuall <hi>love!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I adde but one word yet as to this <hi>Love;</hi> let there be <hi>Love</hi> alſo, <hi>Concord</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> amongſt <hi>bretheren,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Guids</hi> of Flocks. O that wee were ſtudious or ſenſible of the benefits of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> &amp; <hi>Peace,</hi> and would not only hearken unto, but cloſe and proſecute all motions of <hi>Peace,</hi> to repaire our <hi>breaches!</hi> O what a ſad <hi>Behaviour</hi> is it, to bee the Leaders of <hi>Diviſions,</hi> to foment them? If ſome men had endeavoured either to prevent or to heal <hi>Rents</hi> and <hi>Diviſions,</hi> yea if they had not been too inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall both for their riſe and increaſe, then no ſuch <hi>Animoſities, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, heart-burnings, revilings,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſelfe-ſeekings</hi> had been amongſt us, no ſuch <hi>miſrepreſentations</hi> of us, or of our <hi>way,</hi> who are ſtill for the <hi>Liberties</hi> of this poore rent Kirk. But ſince ſo needleſlie and unjuſtlie theſe men in this kirk have and do kythe both by <hi>word</hi> and <hi>write</hi> againſt us, to the great offence of the Reformed Churches abroad, to the further weakning of unſtable <hi>ſoules</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and to the great ſtrengthening of the common <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie;</hi> I muſt needs now hold out ſome paſſages of their <hi>behaviour,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:104070:24"/> or rather <hi>miſbehaviour</hi> carrying a great <hi>Antitheſis</hi> or <hi>Repugnancy</hi> to that <hi>good behaviour</hi> that PAUL deſires in a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> I. Tim. 3. 2. nay parallel their way towards us, with moſt of all the <hi>Directions</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> he preſcribs in theſe three <hi>Epistles,</hi> and then let any impartiall man judge, how far they have ſtarted aſide. I ſhal but inſtance in ſome few particulars.</p>
            <p>Tit. 3. 2. it is ſaid, <hi>Speak evill of no man,</hi> I ask, is this obeyed. when in publick and in private they call us <hi>Malignants, Reſolutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>diſowners of former Principles, Overturners of the worſhip, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and diſcipline of this Kirk,</hi> as the little ſcurrill cankerd <hi>Pamphlet</hi> ſpeaks? To <hi>raile</hi> in the pulpit againſt honeſt peaceable Miniſters, and then to deny it, when they are challenged? as to ſay of ſome of us, there is nothing of God in us, wee were never for a good <hi>turne,</hi> &amp;c. Is this a healing <hi>behaviour?</hi> O no, Theſe and the like maks the <hi>wound</hi> the more incurable; as for example, That vyle <hi>Lybell</hi> ſent up to <hi>London,</hi> ann. 1656 againſt this <hi>Synod,</hi> wherein I may truely ſay, there were as many <hi>Lies</hi> as <hi>Lines;</hi> how can it ſavour of <hi>love</hi> or <hi>peace,</hi> ſince it was ſo full of <hi>untrueths?</hi> If any would own it, hee ought to undergo a moſt ſharp Cenſure. <hi>Love doth not behave it ſelf unſeemlie, it thinketh no evill,</hi> I. Cor. 13. 15: but they dare not own it; The Lord rebuke that <hi>lieing spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I. Tim. 4. 15. it is ſaid, <hi>Give thy ſelf wholly to them,</hi> that is to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>2</label> the neceſſarie duites of thy <hi>Calling.</hi> I ask, is their <hi>gaddings</hi> abroad from their <hi>Callings,</hi> (I ſhall not ſpeak much of ſome of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving themſelves into other mens ſecular <hi>affaires,</hi> though for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Apoſtle, <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 2. 4. condemned by antient <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells,</hi> &amp; by the <hi>Acts</hi> of our Kirk) Their making uncharitable and illegall <hi>Excurſions</hi> into the pariſhes of honeſt brethren, to draw in ſillie <hi>Proſelyts,</hi> and in their trotting up and down, here &amp; there, to brag, That if <hi>Paul</hi> were not of their <hi>judgement,</hi> they would not beleeve him, a pious <hi>Behaviour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I. Tim. 5. 21. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>I Charge thee, that thou obſerve theſe</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>things without prejudice, doing nothing by partialitie.</hi> I ask, if it be a <hi>good behaviour,</hi> to kythe prejudice ſo far againſt a lawfull <hi>Call,</hi> of an honeſt able Miniſter to a deſolat <hi>Place,</hi> and yet neither can or will give any reaſon, why they oppoſe it? Is not this <hi>Partialitie?</hi> yea let <hi>ſoules</hi> ſtarve to death, ere they quite their <hi>prejudice.</hi> Is this a <hi>Behaviour</hi> unbyaſſed, ſelfe-denied, unprejudiced, and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall?</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:104070:24"/>
            <p>I Tim. 5. 22. <hi>Lay hands ſuddenly on no man.</hi> I ask, if it be a <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>4</label> ſutable to that <hi>precept,</hi> to intrude a man upon a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Congregation and Seſſion, wholly againſt their <hi>Call</hi> and <hi>deſire,</hi> and then run-away to the <hi>Powers</hi> to own their diſorderlie <hi>behaviour,</hi> through their <hi>miſinformations</hi> and miſtating the <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion?</hi> Did not the <hi>Arians</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſo? and ſo the <hi>Donatiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> I. Tim. 5. 19. ſaieth, <hi>Againſt an Elder receive not an Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>but before two or three witneſſes.</hi> Yet the <hi>behaviour</hi> of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the little angry <hi>Pamphlet</hi> is, to urge an <hi>inquiſition</hi> upon a Miniſter, without <hi>Libell</hi> or <hi>Accuſer,</hi> or if an <hi>Accuſer</hi> be, hee is ſmoothed with the Name of an <hi>Informer,</hi> and if he ſuccumbe in <hi>probation,</hi> their <hi>Zeale</hi> admits no <hi>retaliation.</hi> Now our diſowning of this dangerous principle and practiſe is one <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as they ſay, that we have fallen from former ſound <hi>Profeſſions</hi> and <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heb. 10. 25. it is ſaid, <hi>Not forſaking the Aſſembling of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>together, as the manner of ſome is.</hi> Notwithſtanding of this <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation,</hi> the <hi>Behaviour</hi> of ſome of our <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> is to abſent themſelves from our <hi>Synods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1. Becauſe they cannot now ſit at the <hi>Helme,</hi> and command all, as they pleaſe. 2. Some of them have been to buſſie to procure <hi>Warrants</hi> that we meete not in <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod,</hi> or if we meete, and take to our conſideration the <hi>grievances</hi> given in againſt their <hi>Novations,</hi> then they can, yea have procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a <hi>warrant</hi> from theſe in <hi>Power</hi> to raiſe us. 3. The <hi>Diotrephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> amongſt them will not aſſemble, becauſe, as one of late co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared our <hi>Synod</hi> to <hi>Baals 400 falſe Prophets,</hi> and himſelf to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cajah,</hi> (when he had little to food his <hi>Hearers</hi> with, but windie <hi>lies,)</hi> and called us <hi>Coetus malignantium.</hi> 4. Some of them abſent themſelves, becauſe they are <hi>Neutrals, Claudicants, wylie,</hi> reſolved to offend none. <hi>(theſe who are neither hote or cold, God will ſpew them out of his mouth,)</hi> Rev. 3. 16. 5. Some of them are ſo chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, <hi>niggard</hi> and <hi>illiberall,</hi> that they will abſent, leſt they ware a penny on publick <hi>affaires,</hi> ſure none of theſe is that <hi>good behaviour</hi> that PAUL wills to be in a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> I. Tim. 3. 2.</p>
            <p>I will give them a touch of Davids <hi>behaviour,</hi> and let any judge and compare that of <hi>David,</hi> with theirs.</p>
            <p>Pſal. 131. Verſ. 2. it is ſaid, <hi>Surely I have behaved and quieted</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>7</label> 
               <hi>my ſelf as a Child that is weaned &amp;c.</hi> I ask, if it be a <hi>Humble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:104070:25"/> to cry up themſelves to be the <hi>ſober party,</hi> the <hi>Godly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> the generalitie of the <hi>Godly in the Land,</hi> &amp;c. Was not this the ordinarie word of the <hi>Denatist,</hi> the <hi>Novatian,</hi> the <hi>Cathariſt. Quod volumus ſanctum est.</hi> what wee will is holie. Uſe they not the ſame arguments againſt us, in their bitter <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> which the old <hi>Separatiſts</hi> uſed againſt <hi>Cyprian, Auguſt.</hi> and <hi>Optatus?</hi> which God-willing ere long I purpoſe to make out at length.</p>
            <p>Pſal. 35. 14. it is ſaid, <hi>I behaved my ſelfe as though hee had</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>8</label> 
               <hi>been my brother or friend</hi> Is it a brotherly <hi>Behaviour,</hi> to count the pluralitie of <hi>Conſtituents</hi> in a <hi>Synod</hi> unſound; becauſe a pluralitie, as the bitter <hi>Pamphlet</hi> hath, &amp; they are not to be intruſted with the <hi>affaires</hi> of Chriſt, and all becauſe they are a pluralitie? Was it a brotherly <hi>behaviour</hi> of a <hi>Non-nemo,</hi> to call our <hi>Synod</hi> a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Combination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> in pſal. 101. 2. profeſſeth, <hi>That hee will behave himſelfe</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>9</label> 
               <hi>wiſely, in a perfect way;</hi> I ask, is it a <hi>Wiſe Courſe</hi> or <hi>behaviour,</hi> to urge <hi>Extrajudiciall Meetings</hi> as the onely meane to heal, ſiſt, and compole our <hi>Differences,</hi> and to purge out <hi>ſcandelous Miniſters</hi> &amp; <hi>Elders?</hi> and theſe <hi>Meetings</hi> to be of equall number of diſſenting in judgement, as to the queſtion anent publick <hi>Reſolutions?</hi> and theſe <hi>Delegats</hi> from <hi>Synods,</hi> to have a <hi>Negative voice</hi> over <hi>Synods</hi> ſo long at leaſt, till compoſing and purging bee cloſed? Is this a <hi>Court</hi> of Chriſts inſtitution? or is it not rather more then the <hi>Prelatick Power</hi> over <hi>Synods?</hi> How excentrick is this to our eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed <hi>Government</hi> both by acts of this Kirk, and Laws of this Land, let any judge?</p>
            <p>IT is ſaid <hi>Iſai. 52. 13. Behold my ſervant ſhall deale prudently.</hi> I <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>10</label> ask, if it be a prudent zealous <hi>Behaviour</hi> of ſome of theſe men, ſtill to cry out for <hi>purging,</hi> when as their own <hi>Principles</hi> &amp; <hi>actings,</hi> cloſlie obſtruct that working? That is, (according to them,) <hi>Though a Judicatorie proceed never ſo conſcientiouſly and juſtly, yet the Party Cenſured is ſtill the Supream Judge on earth, of all their proceedings, and of his own actings alſo, in relation to their ſentence, and till he be convinced, hee muſt ſuffer nothing, but counteract at his pleaſure.</hi> ſo acted the <hi>Arian</hi> after the 1. of <hi>Nice,</hi> ſo the <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> after that of <hi>Dort,</hi> ſo the old <hi>Donatiſt</hi> after the third Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſo do the <hi>Socinians</hi> now. And after the example of theſe <hi>Remonſtrators</hi> ſo may any now, to be purged out, and ſo might all theſe do who were lawfullie depoſed by our <hi>Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104070:25"/> whereas it is the conſtant <hi>judgement</hi> of ſound <hi>Divines,</hi> that even an unjuſt <hi>Sentence</hi> (though <hi>in foro interno</hi> it do not obliege the <hi>Conſcience)</hi> yet <hi>in foro externo,</hi> it being the <hi>act</hi> of a lawfull <hi>Judicatory,</hi> it is ſo far valid, that a man cannot in reaſon deny <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to it, at leaſt <hi>paſſive;</hi> for in this caſe, wee hold the <hi>Party grieved</hi> ought to ſubmit to the <hi>ſentence,</hi> not onely till the <hi>Appeal</hi> bee diſcuſſed, but alſo after, if the <hi>Appeal</hi> bee diſcuſſed againſt him. And as the late <hi>Review of Protesters not &amp;c.</hi> hath, which if he ſubmit not unto, he ſinnes againſt God, that is, in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the lawfull ſtanding <hi>Authority</hi> of the Kirk, by making a <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> by declyning that whereto God calls him. Now what a <hi>Scandalous behaviour</hi> (to keep the terme of my TEXT,) is their anſwere to this? to wit, <hi>That our Kirk of</hi> Scotland <hi>is now unſound,</hi> ſee p. 116. of that bitter BITT. Let any judge, if this expoſeth not their <hi>Mother-kirk</hi> to the ludibrie of all <hi>Adverſaries?</hi> The Authors cited by the <hi>Review,</hi> p. 117. and elſwhere ſay, <hi>That in caſe of difference of judgement between the Judge and the Party con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the nature of a ſentence pronounced, and when neither of them is able to convince the other, the judgement of the Judge ought to carry it, as to the Parties paſſive Obedience, and that hee is not to counteract untill another Judicatorie repeal that ſentence.</hi> For this <hi>Paſſive ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> as is well marked by them, is a notable meane between <hi>ſinfull Obedience,</hi> and <hi>ſchiſmaticall Counteracting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I. Cor. 13. 7. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes there, <hi>That Charitie beleeveth all things,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>11</label> 
               <hi>hopeth all things, indureth all things.</hi> I ask, is it a Charitable <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion,</hi> to call all the means wee have uſed for healing &amp; union, in our papers, declarations, meetings &amp; conferences, <hi>meer Mock-remedies,</hi> if ſo be that wee will not diſown theſe two lawfull <hi>Generall Aſſemblies,</hi> ann. 1651. 1652? although our <hi>Profeſsions</hi> who own them ſtill, are not to impoſe on their <hi>judgements,</hi> ſo that in <hi>practicables</hi> they joine with us. And that wee are content theſe <hi>Cenſures</hi> be taken off (which ſtill wee think were juſt) providing there be no counteracting.</p>
            <p>Pag. 67. Is it a ſutable or Goſpel-like <hi>Behaviour,</hi> ſo far to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>12</label> ſpitt into their <hi>Mothers</hi> face, as to urge a <hi>defection</hi> from the <hi>Trueths</hi> profeſſed in this Church, by petitioning for a vaſt and illegall <hi>Toleration?</hi> and to call it a <hi>Gospel priviledge,</hi> and the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers</hi> of it, the <hi>Wel-affected,</hi> although they joine with the <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> petitionating the ſame? yea to owne the <hi>quakers</hi> as to that.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104070:26"/> as is in the 7 page of their ſcurrilous <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon the worthy Teſtimony of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> Presbyterie.</p>
            <p>Page 67. Is it a <hi>peaceable</hi> and <hi>Gospel-behaviour,</hi> to call the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer </seg>13</label> 
               <hi>Pillars</hi> of this Kirk <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> for giving that juſt anſwere to the Parliaments <hi>Querie,</hi> which all ſound <hi>Divines</hi> beyond ſeas have owned as orthodox and juſt? and of late in <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>D. Voëtius</hi> in formall words had this expreſſion of theſe <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> written in a <hi>Letter</hi> to a friend of mine, <hi>Theſe peeviſh men ſeem to be poſſeſſed with judiciall blindneſſe, ſince worſe men the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any in</hi> Scotland, <hi>were bound to defend their Countrey and what is deare to them, against all Forraigne unjust invaſion, all having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like intereſt, as to that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then duly conceive, That ſuch <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſutable behaviours,</hi> may be a meane both ſtrong &amp; ſad, to unchurch this NATION, <hi>to make our Sun go down even at noone-day, to put a bill of divorce into our hands,</hi> that for theſe, the Lord may in juſtice lay us aſide, and tell us, <hi>that hee hath no more work to be done by or amongſt us.</hi> But if the Lord be at this time, in anſwere to the prayers of his <hi>ſervants,</hi> as would ſeem, <hi>to open a door of hope,</hi> let us relinquiſh and caſt off what ever it be, that may oppoſe or hinder ſo ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable a <hi>mercie.</hi> And to that end, let us endeavour, <hi>to ſerve one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in love, to beare the infirmities of the weake, to build up each other in our most holy faith,</hi> that wee may be diligent in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciencious performance of the ſeverall duties of our <hi>Callings;</hi> that we may keep our ſelves unſpoted, or tainted with the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raptions</hi> of theſe backſliding times, ſuch as are <hi>Popiſh deluſions, doating on errors, ſinfull ſeparations, endleſſe diviſions, Profainneſſe, Prelatike imparitie</hi> too palpable in ſome Miniſters, even in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed <hi>paritie,</hi> &amp; the too buſſie <hi>advancement of ſelfe, or private inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts.</hi> Now for the ſpeedy and right avoiding of theſe and ſuch ſpirituall <hi>Rocks,</hi> let us ſeriouſlie lay to heart theſe following powerfull <hi>Inſtructions,</hi> ſo much conducing to the furtherance of a <hi>Godlie</hi> and <hi>learned Ministery.</hi> Which were in the Antient kirk required to be had by heart, and anſwered unto, at the ORDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NATION of <hi>Intrants,</hi> as an Amuler or preſervative for <hi>Good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>—I. Tim.</hi> 4. 7. Exerciſe thy ſelf unto godlineſſe, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 4. 12. be thou an example to beleevers, in word, in converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in faith, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 4. 16. Take heed unto thy ſelf, and unto the doctrine:</item>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:104070:26"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 6. 12. Fight the good fight of faith. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 6. 13. 14. I charge thee in the ſight of God, that thou keep this Commandement without spot. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. Tim.</hi> 6. 20. O Timothy, keep that which is committed to thy trust, avoiding prophane and vain bablings, and oppoſitions of ſciences, falſly ſo called.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 1. 6. Stirre up the gift of God that is in thee.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 1. 13. Hold faſt the forme of ſound words, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 1. 11. That good thing which was committed unto thee, keep by the Holy Ghoſt which dwelleth in us.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 2. 22. Flee alſo youthfull luſts: but follow Righteouſneſſe, Faith, Charity, peace, with them that call on the Name of the Lord out of a pure heart.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 4. 2. Preach the Word, be inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 4. 5. But watch thou in all things, endure afflictions, do the work of an Evangeliſt, make full proofe of thy Miniſtery.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>I Tim.</hi> 4. 13. 14 15. Give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine. 14. Neglect not the gift that is in thee. 15. Meditae upon theſe things, give thy ſelfe wholly to them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 2. 14. Charging them before the Lord, that they ſtrive not about words, to no profite, but to the ſubverting of the hearers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. Tim.</hi> 3. 14. But continue thou in the things, which thou haſt learned, and haſt been aſſured of.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9. Holding faſt the faithfull word, as hee hath been taught, that he may able &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 1. But speak thou the things which become ſound doctrine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 8. Theſe things I will that thou affirme conſtantly, that they which have beleeved in God, might be carefull to maintain good works.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 10. How that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, reject.</item>
            </list>
            <q>Glory be to thee O God!</q>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
